<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two discourses of Master Frances Guicciardin vvhich are wanting in the thirde and fourth bookes of his Historie, in all the Italian, Latin, and French coppies heretofore imprinted; which for the worthinesse of the matter they containe, were published in those three languages at Basile 1561. And are now for the same cause doone into English.</title>
            <title>Loci duo. Polyglot</title>
            <author>Guicciardini, Francesco, 1483-1540.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839270</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3676</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02334)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3676)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 319:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two discourses of Master Frances Guicciardin vvhich are wanting in the thirde and fourth bookes of his Historie, in all the Italian, Latin, and French coppies heretofore imprinted; which for the worthinesse of the matter they containe, were published in those three languages at Basile 1561. And are now for the same cause doone into English.</title>
                  <title>Loci duo. Polyglot</title>
                  <author>Guicciardini, Francesco, 1483-1540.</author>
                  <author>Guicciardini, Francesco, 1483-1540. Historia d'Italia. Supplements.</author>
                  <author>Jones, William, fl. 1594-1595.</author>
                  <author>Jones, William, Sir, 1566-1640.</author>
                  <author>Petrarca, Francesco, 1304-1374.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For William Ponsonbie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Loci duo.</note>
                  <note>Translator's preface signed: W.I., i.e. William Jones, fl. 1594-5; sometimes attributed to Sir William Jones.</note>
                  <note>French, English, Latin, and Italian in parallel columns.</note>
                  <note>"Three sonnets of Petrarch", verso title page.</note>
                  <note>Even page numbers are on rectos.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Temporal power --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:1"/>
            <p>TWO Diſcourſes of Maſter Frances Guicciardin, vvhich are wanting in the thirde and fourth <hi>Bookes of his Hiſtorie, in all the Italian,</hi> Latin, and French Coppies here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore imprinted; <hi>Which for the worthineſſe of the matter they</hi> containe, were publiſhed in thoſe three Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages at Baſile 1561. And are now for the ſame cauſe doone into Engliſh.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>serpent and cross</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at London for William</hi> Ponſonbie. 1595.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnets">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:2"/>
            <head>Three Sonnets of Petrarch.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Fiamma dal ciel, &amp;c. Son. 106.</head>
               <l>1 LEwd whore that from the meaneſt ſtate of life,</l>
               <l>vnt' others fal and ſpoile waſt beaſtly bred,</l>
               <l>Whoſe whole delight doth ſtand on hateful ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Let fire from heauen be poured on thy head.</l>
               <l>Oh neaſt of ſinne, wherein now hatched is,</l>
               <l>That euill which through al the world is ſpread,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Venus playes her maiſters prize amiſſe,</l>
               <l>with Wine, with eaſe. and bowſie Bacchus eke,</l>
               <l>Old fooles, yong maids, beſtride thy ſtreetes in blis,</l>
               <l>Daunſing their roundes with Sathans dam vnmeeke,</l>
               <l>With bellowes, fire, with glaſſes to behold</l>
               <l>Their ſhame, that they do ſenceleſſe in thee ſeeke.</l>
               <l>Simple thy ſource: moſt ſinfull thou, now olde;</l>
               <l>his vvrath therefore vvill God of heauen vnfolde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>L'auard Babilonia, &amp;c. Son. 107.</head>
               <l>2 NOw Babilon hath fild her greedy ſacke,</l>
               <l>With wrath from Heaune, ſact vp with filthy ſin</l>
               <l>Which rents the ſame, to break at laſt thy backe,</l>
               <l>That fauor none from Ioue dooft ſeeke to vvin.</l>
               <l>From Pallas none. To Venus, Bacchus, he</l>
               <l>(in luſt to ſwim, and ſinke vp to the chinne)</l>
               <l>Oblations thine, and rights deuoted be.</l>
               <l>Redreſſe thereof my pined hart doth pray,</l>
               <l>(That helpe at hand, that golden helpe foreſee)</l>
               <l>Reſtored Church, fel Idols dire decaie,</l>
               <l>Recured Faith, al falſhood put to flight;</l>
               <l>The man of ſinne, to beare no more the ſway,</l>
               <l>The golden World reſtorde, and euery Wight</l>
               <l>With fruites of grace, and heauenly dainties dight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Fontana di dolore, &amp;c. Son. 108.</head>
               <l>3 THou ſource of griefe, thou den of wrath and ire,</l>
               <l>Schoole of deceit, old errors hydeous haunt:</l>
               <l>Earſt Rome, but now fell Babel, ſet on fire</l>
               <l>With burning brands, ſuch as olde Orchus Aunt</l>
               <l>With fury flung, the hart of man t'inflame.</l>
               <l>Thou forge of filth, thou vertues fal, auaunt,</l>
               <l>Sinke ſhall thy pride, thy ſinne, and thou, with ſhame.</l>
               <l>How can it be but that thy Chriſt thy king</l>
               <l>Will beat thee downe with al thy brandes of blame,</l>
               <l>Abate thy hornes, and thee to meekneſſe bring,</l>
               <l>Thou, that vvhilome of lovv beginning grew,</l>
               <l>And wonted was vvith lowlie ſound to ſing;</l>
               <l>With vertues olde, thy glories old renew,</l>
               <l>Leaſt Conſtantine returne thy vvrack to revv.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, hauing gotten the ſighte ſo theſe two diſcourſes by meanes of a good friend that did lend me the ſame in three La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, the Latin, Italian &amp; French, imprinted at <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil:</hi> I thought it a good labor to put them into Engiſh for the matter contained in the ſame, &amp; eſpecially in the larger of them, wherein you ſhall find a notable diſcourſe of anexcellent Author, written long ſince, and ſetting foorth very liuely how the Sea of Rome did enlarge their iuriſdiction and Territories, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſubtile means, as alſo by the ſuppoſed donation of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great to pope <hi>Silueſter.</hi> And bicauſe they are left out in al the printed books of <hi>Fr. Guicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardin</hi> his ſtorye, ſome ſcruple did ſtay me a while to publiſhe the ſame leaſt they might bee ſuppoſed to bee of ſome other authour. Wherein I haue ſithence byn vndoubtedly reſolued, by ſom perſons of honor and good calling, who both haue ſeene the ſame in the <hi>Original</hi> at <hi>Florence</hi> written of the authors own hand, &amp; yet in the cuſtody of <hi>Laurence Guicciar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> and haue had copies of the ſame from the <hi>Guicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardines.</hi> So as I dare affirm on my credit, that the ſam were of the authors, and left out of purpoſe, becauſe they diſcouer ſuch matter againſt the popes vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as in the reading of them thou maiſt perceiue. I deſire but thy fauourable acceptance of my labour, wiſhing thee al happineſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London <date>the 16. of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, 1595.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy friend to vſe, W.I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:3"/>
            <head>LECTORI.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nuadendis occupandiſque Jmperijs, iuris ſaepe color initiò quaeri ſolet: ſtabilita verò fundata<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſemel tyrannide, vetera illa ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia quantum poteſt obruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, lex tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regia nudè, &amp; veluti <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> obtenditur, in contemptoris legib. maieſtatis per duellionum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vindicatur. Jta<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter magis &amp; ingenuè quàm caute Paulus III. cum de ſumma ipſius poteſtate aliquando inter fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liares mentio incideret, ridere illos ſolitus erat vt ſcholaſticos &amp; rerum rudes, qui à Chriſto eam tam anxiè repeterent, cuius ſe poſſeſſionem vel ſolam, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum et firmiſſimum titulum habere dicebat, quam viribus opibuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſummis, ciuitatibus munitiſſimis, &amp; potentiſſimorum principum ſibi coniurantium auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio tueri ac defendere poſſet. Prudentius etiam Jtalo rum pars maxima, quae pontificem Rom. non vti De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aliquem, aut Dei vicariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob fulmina illa, quibus iam pene totus inermis eſt: ſed vt principem viris, armis, vrbibus, caſtellis, foederibuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> potentiſſimum reueretur &amp; obſeruat. Nos verò quos ille vt pueru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los ſola vanae religionis larua perterret, quibuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vt venalitijs mancipijs pro arbitrio abutitur, ſcire ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando par eſt, quo iure, quáue iniuria tam duro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clementi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> domino ſeruiamus: non vt tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taci bellum aliquod ſeruile moueamus, ſed vt ingenui nati, &amp; quorum maiores ſeruitutem illam non ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erent,
<pb facs="tcp:3676:3"/>
vindicibus tandem idoneis vel tertia aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſemel amiſſam libertatem &amp; ſtrenuè recuperemus &amp; fortiter retineamus conſeruemuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>. Natales por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro noſtros vel ab eiuſdem domini familia aliqua ſalte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex parte repetere licet, ex qua eſt hoc quidem manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium, ſed frugi admodum, &amp; manumiſſione digniſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum cuius etiam hac in refidem herus infideliſsimus per alligatos obruere conatus eſt. Nos tabulas quaſi ex naufragio, aut potius ex rogo viſpellionum mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus extortas omnibus reddimus. Quarum fidem &amp; vindicum ſatis perſpecta integritas, &amp; auctoris ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, &amp; loci ipſius, vnde dolo malo detractae ſunt, vel ſola inſpectio ſic aſſerunt, vt de ea nemo bonus iuſtè dubitare poſſit. Reliquum eſt, vt hoc beneficio pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter &amp; ſerio vtamur fruamur<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ne ſi nos ob preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um participandum iterum quodammodo venire pati amur, non eadem poſthac ſpes libertatis affulgeat et perpetua ſeruitute, dignisſima etiam grauioribus flagris mancipia premamur.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:4"/>
            <head>Deux diſcours de M. Francois Guicciardin, leſquels defaillent és III. &amp; IIII. és liures de ſon Hiſtoire en tous les exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaires tant Italiens, Latins, que Francois, par cy deuant imprimez.</head>
            <opener>Retirez de l'original, &amp; publiez nouuellement pour le merite des choſes y contenues.</opener>
            <head>AV LECTEVR.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>'IL y a artifice en ce monde auquella preud ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie &amp; fidelité ſo it requiſe, certainement on peut dire que l'impreſsion des liures eſt le premier. Car les grands profits qui en reuiennent, quand elle eſt maniée comme il appartient, ſont contrebalancez de tant d'incommoditez &amp; de dangers qui enſuyuent l'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus d'icelle, que le tout eſtant comme en la main &amp; diſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſation des hommes, quelques vns ſemblent auoir eu occaſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on de reuoquer en doute, s'il euſt eſté meilleur &amp; plus expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient que ceſte inuention ne fuſt iamais venue en vſage. Or ceſte fidelité ne conſiſte pas ſeulement en ce que ceux qui font profeſsion de ceſt art, ne publient liuers inutiles ou mauuais (qui ſont toutefois deux poincts qu'ils doiuent ſongneuſement garder) mais auſsi qu'ayans en main ce qui aura ſemble pouuoir apporter proufit au public par l'aduis de ceux qui en peuuent bien iuger, ils ne facent point trop les ingenieux és labeurs d'autruy, changeants ou retran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chans ce qui n'eſt à leur fantaſie &amp; appetit, mais qu'ils repre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſentent fidelement &amp; religieuſement leurs exemplaires. Car quant à moy, pour pluſieurs conſiderations que ce lieu ne puet pas porter, ie ſuis de ceſte opinion, &amp; croy que pluſieurs n'en iugeront pas autreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, qu'il vaudroit mieux ſupprimer du tout vn auteur, qu'en le publiant abuſer ainſi de ſes intentions. Cependant ie ne doute pas que les fautes qui ſe commettent en ceſt endroit, viennent le plus ſouuet de ceux qui ou fourniſſent liberalement de leurs exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaires, ou bien en font traffique &amp; marchandiſe ordinaire (indigne certes d'un homme de lettres, lequel contre le precepte de meſnage ruſtique de Caton, doit eſtre en ceſt
<pb facs="tcp:3676:4"/>
endroict pluſtoſt acheteur que vendeur) tant y a que de quelque coſte que cela vienne, il eſt grandement à blaſmer voire digne de punition publique: meſmement quand tel abus ſe commet en liures plus authentiques &amp; deſquels on employe couſtumierement la foy &amp; l'autorité. Mais pleuſt à Dieu que nous nu eſsions point ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t d'occaſions de nous plaindre de ce malheur, qui n'eſt que par trop frequent &amp; commun aux vns et aux autres. Ie ne veux rien dire de S. Ciprian de Rome &amp; de quelques liures de Tertullien pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liez à Paris, deſquels toutesfois pluſieurs gens de bien ſe plaignent: mais ie diray ſeulement que ces fragments de l'Hiſtoire de meſsire Francois Guicciardin nous donnent grande occaſion de nous deffier de beaucoup d'autres. Or qu'ils ne ſoyent vrayement de luy &amp; n'ayant eſté retra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chez par ci deuant de ſon exemplaire, outre l'aſſeurance qu'on peut auoir en la prend'hommie &amp; loyauté de celuy qui les a extraits &amp; communiquez, la phraſe ſcule de l'autheur qui luy eſt preſque particuliere, (argument certain &amp; comme infallible en telle choſe) en fera plaine &amp; entiere foy à ceux qui en voudront iuger ſans paſsion. Outre ce que (comme vne fineſſe malicieuſe ne ſe peut deſguiſer tellement, qu'en fin elle ne ſe deſcouure à la confuſion de ſon ouurier) on n'a peu ſi bien remplir ce qui s'enſuit en l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hiſtoire, meſmement pour le regard du premier de ces deux lieux, qu'on nevoye a l'oeil qu'il y a quelque deffaut: le quel ſe trouuera iuſteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rempli par ces pieces, qu'on recongnoiſtra incontinent en auoir eſté retirées, ou pluſtoſt deſchirees &amp; deſrobees.</p>
            <p>Maintenant les ayants comme rachetees de la main de leurs ennemis, nous les repreſentons en toutes ces la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues eſquelles le reſte de ceſte hiſtoire a eſté par cy deuant pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliée, à fin qu'vn chaſcun puiſſe remplir, ſi bon luy ſemble, ſon exemplaire de ce deffaut: qui eſt de telle conſequence, qu'eſtans les aduis y contenus bien receus, &amp; les moyens contraires bien pratiquez, nous eſperons, auec l'aide de Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eu, qu'en brief il s'en pourra enſuyure en Europe vne paix &amp; tranquilité vniuerſelle.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:5"/>
            <head>Dui luoghi dell hiſtoria di M. Franceſco Guicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardini: L'vno de quali è mutato nel terzo libro à carte <hi>91.</hi> b. nella ſtampa Venetiana in quarta forma. L'altro del tutto tolto via nel quarto libro à carte <hi>119.</hi> di detta ſtampa.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vanto che l'hiſtoria di M. Franceſco Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciardini, per teſtimonio d'ogni intelligente è tenuta utile &amp; profitteuole, tanto piu ſon da eſsere biaſmati quelli, &amp; da riprendere la lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro infedelta, i quali ſon ſtati ſi arditi &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuntuoſi che non ſolamente l'hanno corrotta, ma etiamdio ſtracciatone nia queſti dui pezzi: lun de quali è di tanta co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequenza &amp; importanza, che non ſolo è expediente il leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerlo, ma è neceſsario à ciaſcheduno l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>intendere la contenu ta verità in quel diſcorſo marauiglioſamente diſcoperta dal Guicciardino, &amp; particolarmente ſopra tutti li altri ſenza ueruna paſſione narrata. Il che è ſtato cauſa, che ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendo ricouerato queſti duifragmenti quaſi come dal fuoco, da chi o per paura o per maluagità l'haueua naſcoſti &amp; quaſi ſepolti, noi te li diamo in tutte quelle lingue, nelle quali fino a queſt'hora preſente l'hiſtoria del detto auctore è ſtata da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta alla luce: riportando ci della uerità di queſti luoghi, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma alla conſcienza di quelli, appo i quali ſi ritroua l'origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale di detto Guicciardini intero: &amp; appreſſo à tutte le per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone ſcienziate &amp; intendenti, le quali potranno per loro ſteſ ſe riconoſcere in queſti tali luoghi la medeſima lingua &amp; il medeſimo ſtilo del Guicciardino, di che ſi vede compoſta tut
<pb facs="tcp:3676:5"/>
ta l'hiſtoria, &amp; nedere quanto ella ne rimanga difettoſaper lo mancamento di queſtapicciola parte. A queſte coſe ag giugeremo anchora la molta fede, che per la ſua ſincerita, &amp; per altre lodeuoli qualità merita che ſe le preſte la perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, da chi cotali luoghi ci ſono ſtati dati à fine che li commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichiamo à tuttigli amatoridel uero, ſe mifoſſe coſi lecito il nominarla, come mi è conueneuole il tenerla celata. Hor per non perder tempo inprouar coſa che per ſe ſteſſa è chia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsima à chi non ha corrotta la uiſta, in una parola diremo, il noſtro deſiderio eſſere, Lector cariſsimo, che ogn'huono li legga, &amp; ne facci il ſuo profitto ſenza abuſare la propria conſcienza di ſi fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aduertimento.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:6"/>
            <head>Lieu changé au troſie me liure de l'hiſtoire de <hi>M. Francois Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciardin. I.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ais il ne peut euiter les infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques, qui trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blerent grandement ſa maiſon auec exemples Tragiques, vilenies &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>autez horribles, voire meſmes en toute region tant barbare qu'elle puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe eſtre.</p>
            <p>Car ayant dés lors qu'il fut eſleu Pape, deliberé de tranſporter toute la gran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deur temporelle en la per ſonne du duc de Candie ſon fils aiſné, le Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal de Valence, qui d'un eſprit to talement eſlong né de la profeſsion eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtique, aſpiroit au ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niement des armes ne pouuant endurer que ſon frere occupaſt ce lieu ſur luy, &amp; d'abondant porta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fort impatiemment qu'il euſt meilleure part en la bonne grace de madame Lucrece leur ſeur co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, pouſſé de rage d'a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour &amp; d'ambition (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guillons &amp; miniſtres puiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſans
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3676:7"/>
ſans à toute meſcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cete) fit tuer par une nuict le Duc ſon frere, lors qu'il cheuauchoit ſeul par la ville de Romme, &amp; puis ietter ſecretement dans la riuiere du Tybre. Il eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toit encor bruit ſi telle en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ormité ſe peult croire) qu'en l'amour demadame Lucrece, ily auoit concur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence, non ſeulement des deux freres, mais du pere meſme lequel ayant dés le comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cement de ſon pontificat retirè ſa fille d'auec ſon premier mary, qu'il eſtimoit eſtre deue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu trop petit compagno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pour ſon degré, &amp; de puis l'ayant mariée a lean Sforze ſigneur de Peſaro, ne pouuant encor ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter d'auoir le mary pour compagnon, il rompit ce ſecond mariage ia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommé, ayant à ceſte fin fait prouuer par faux teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moignage deuant les iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges que luymeſme auoit deleguez, &amp; puis confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer par ſentence &amp; iuge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, que Iean eſtoit de nature froide, &amp; du tout inhabile aux oeuures de mariage, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:6"/>
            <head>A place altered in the third <hi>Book of his Hiſtory, in the</hi> 91. pag, in the ſecond ſide of the pa, <hi>after the impreſsion of Venice; the</hi> Hiſtorie being imprinted in quarto.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et coulde he not auoide the euils which hapned in his own family, which did great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly troble his houſe, with tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical examples, with luſt, and horible crueltie, the like wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of hath not beene ſeene in any barbarous nation: For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in his firſt entrance into the Papacie, determined, to tranſport al temporal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to the perſon of the duke of <hi>Candie</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, the Cardinall of <hi>Valentia,</hi> whoe (carrying a mind alienate, &amp; repugnante to Eccleſiaſticall profeſſion and did aſpire to the managing of arms) could not endure that his brother ſhould obtaine that place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: and moreouer bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring verie impatiently, that hee had better part in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Lady <hi>Lucretia,</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to them both, pricked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with the rage of loue, and ambition (forcible mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3676:7"/>
in all kind of miſchiefe) cauſed the Duke his brother to be murthered in a night, as he rid alone through <hi>Rome</hi> and afterwards to be caſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretlie into the Riuer <hi>Tiber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the ſame time the report was (if ſo foule an enormitie may be beleeued) that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the twoe brethren did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the loue of the Ladye <hi>Lucrecia,</hi> but the father like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: whoe was no ſooner made Pope, but he tooke his daughter from her firſt huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (as one farre inferiour to him in degree) and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes married her to <hi>Iohn Sforza</hi> Lord of <hi>Piſaro:</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to brooke her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band for his Corriual, did like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe diſſolue this ſecond ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, already finiſhed: And to the end the ſame might bee done vnder ſome colour, hee ſuborned falſe witneſſes, to make proofe before Iudges, delegate and choſen by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that the Lord <hi>Iohn</hi> was cold by nature, and altogither vnapt for copulation, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="part">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3676:6"/>
            <head>Franciſci Guicciardini locus primus re ponendus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro III. folio 121. <hi>verſu.</hi> 33.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>EC tamen potuit calamitates dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticas uitare, quae tragicis exemplis, libidine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, atque immanitate plus quàm barbara, eius domum conturbarunt. Nam cum ab uſque ſui pontificatus auſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciis omnem ciuilem poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in Candianum ducem ſuorum liberoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> natu maxi mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vertere ſtatuiſſet, &amp; Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinus cardinalis animo prorſus à ſacris alieno ad re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> militarem totus aſpiraret, nec ferre' poſſet hunc locu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi à fratre praereptum iri: eundem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris Lucretiae amore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri, libidine at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ambitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, valentibus ad quoduis ſcelus ſtimulis, incitatus, fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trem noctu Romae inequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantem, necari fecit, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3676:7"/>
in Tyberim clàm abiici.</p>
            <p>Ad hoc fama fuit (ſi tamen tantum nefas fidem meretur) non modò fratres duos, verumetiam patrem ipſum in eiuſdem Lucretiae amores conſpiraſſe: qui ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulac ad pontificatum aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptus eſt, eam à primo marito quaſi tanta dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te tunc inferiore, abreptam Ioanni Sfortiae Piſaurenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um domino copulauit: ſed ne hunc quidem riuale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, matrimonium iam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum diſſoluit: verum vt id aliquo fieret colore, cum coram iudicibus à ſe delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, Ioannem natura frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, atque ad rem venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am prorſus ineptum, per fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſos teſtes comprobaſſet, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum ſententiis id confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mari voluit, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:6"/>
            <head>¶ Luogo mutato nel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terzo libro a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te 91. b.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>A non potette gia fuggire gl'infortunij domeſtici, e quali per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutbarano la caſa ſua con eſſempij tragici, &amp; con libidine &amp; crudel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tà horribile etiamdio in ogni barbara regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: per che hauendo in fino daprincipio del ſuo po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teficato diſegnato di volgere tutta la gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezza temporale al Du ca di Candia ſuo primo genito, il Cardinale di Valenza il quale di a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo totalmente alieno dalla profeſſione ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotale aſpiraua all eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſercitio delle arme, non potendo tolerare che queſto loco gli foſſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupato dal fratello: im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiente oltre à queſto, che egli haueſſe piu par
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3676:7"/>
te di lui nell'amore di mado<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na Lucretia ſorella commune, in citato dalia libidine, &amp; dall ambitione, miniſtri potentî ad ogni gran ſceleratezza, lo fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vna notte, che ei caualcaua ſolo per Roma, amazzare, &amp; poi gittare nel fiume del Teue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſegretame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. Era medeſima me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te fama, ſe però è degna di crederſi tanta enormità, che nell amore di mado<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia concorreſſino no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te i duo fratelli, ma etiamdio il padre medeſimo: il quale haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dola come fu fatto pontefice, leuata dal primo marito come diuentato inferiore al ſuo gra do, &amp; maritatala a Giouanni Sforza ſignore di Peſaro, non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>partando d'hauere anco il marito per riuale, diſſoluè il matrimonio gia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumato, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uendo fatto innanzia giudici delegati da lui prouare co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe teſtimonianze, &amp; di poi con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fermare per ſentenza che Gio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uanni era per natura frigido, &amp; impotenteal coito. Affliſſe ſopra modo, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3676:8"/>
            <head>Diſcours retranché, du qua trieſme liure de la meſme hiſtoire. II.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Our la declaration de la quelle choſe &amp; de beaucoup d'au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres depuis aduenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, la matiere requiert que ie die quel droict l'Egliſe ha ſur la terre de la Romagne &amp; ſur plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs autres leſquelles elle a poſſedées en diuers temps, ou poſſede encor à preſent: &amp; par quels moyens, eſtant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mierement inſtitué &amp; eſtabli pour l'adminiſtration pure &amp; ſimple des choſes ſpirituelles, elle eſt paruenue aux eſtats &amp; principautez mondaines.</p>
            <p>Pareillement auſsi, que comme choſe connexe à ce propos, i'expoſe quels debats &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions ſont ſuruenues en di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers temps pour ceſte occaſion &amp; autres, entre les papes &amp; les empereurs.</p>
            <p>Les eueſques de Romme, deſquels ſainct Pierre fut le premier, ayans leur puiſſance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3676:9"/>
&amp; authorité fondée de Ieſus Chriſtés choſes ſpirituelles, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans au reſte grands de chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té, humilité, patience d'eſprit &amp; de miracles, furent à leur commencement, non ſeule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment du tont deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uez de puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance temporelle, mais encor perſecutez d'icelle, &amp; demeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerent par un lon temps peu ou quaſi point cogneus, n'eſtant leur nom par autre choſe plus manifeſte que par ſupplices, leſquels ils euduroient egalle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment auec ceux qui les enſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiènt.</p>
            <p>Car combien que pour la multitude infinie de diuerſes nations &amp; profeſſions qui e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoientlors à Romme, on print peu garde quelques fois à leur progrez &amp; aduancement, &amp; qu'aucuns des emperenrs ne les perſecutaſſent ſinon entant que leurs actions publiques ſembloient ne ſe pouuoir diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muler ou paſſer ſous ſilence: toutes fois aucuns autres on par cruanté, ou pour l'amour &amp;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3676:10"/>
zele qu'ils auoient à leurs dieux exercoient fort rigoureuſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution à l'encontre d'eux, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me aucteurs de nouelles ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions &amp; deſtructeurs de la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vraye religion.</p>
            <p>En ceſt eſtat ils continuerent eſtants copendant grandement renommez pour leur pauureté uoluntaire, ſaincteté de uie &amp; martires, iuſqu'au temps du pa pe Sylueſtre: ſous lequel eſtant l'Empereur Conſtantin conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti à la foy Chreſtienne, meu par la bonne uie et par les miracles qui ſe uoioient continuelleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t en eux qui faiſoient profeſsion du nom de Ieſus Chriſt, les E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſques demeuroient paiſibles &amp; aſſeurez des grands perils eſquels ils s'eſtoient veus par l'eſpace d'enuiron trois cents ans, auec libertè de faire exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cice publique de leur religion &amp; ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Dont pour la reuerence de leurs couſtumes, pour les ſaincts commandemens que contient en ſoy noſtre religion, &amp; pour la promptitude qui eſt és hommes à ſuiure, ou par am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bition
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3676:11"/>
le plus ſouuent, ou par crainte, quelq fois a l'exemple de leur prince, la Chreſlienté commenca à s'eſpandre &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plifier par tout merueilleuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; par meſme moyen comm enca ausſi à diminuer l'ancienne pauureté des eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſtiques, d'autant que Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tin ayant edifié à Romme les e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſes de ſainct Iean de Latran, ſainct Pierre du Vatican, de S. Paul, &amp; pluſieurs autres en di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers lieux, il les doua non ſeule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meur de riches uaiſſeaux &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namenns, mais encor, à ſin qu à l'aduenir elles cuſſent de quoy eſtre conſeruées, entretenues &amp; renouuelées, auſsi pour l'entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenement de ceux qui faiſoyent le ſeruice diuin, les enrichit de pluſieurs poſſeſsions &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</p>
            <p>Depuis ce temps, pluſieurs ſe perſuadans qu'auec aumoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; legs il leur ſeroit aifé d'ac querir le royaume des cieux, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difierent &amp; douerent quelques autres egliſes, ou à celles qui e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoyent ia edifiées donnerent partie de leurs richeſſes: voyre meſmes, ou par certaine loy ou
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3676:12"/>
par couſtume inueterée, enſuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uant l'exemple du vieil Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, chaſcnn d'eux payoit à l'egliſe la diſme du fruict &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenu de ſes propres biens.</p>
            <p>A quoy faire ils eſtoyent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citez d'autant plus gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ardeur &amp; courage, quils uoioient au commencement que les gens d'egliſe, hors mis ce qu'ils ſe reſeruoyent pour uiure aſſez frugalement &amp; moderement, employans le ſurplus de ces biens partie en la fabrique &amp; paremenr des egliſes, partie en oeuures pitoyables &amp; charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, n'eſtant encor entré en leurs coeurs l'orguoeil &amp; l'ambi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>L'eueſque de Romme lors eſtoit recongneu par tous les Chreſtiens pour ſuperieur de toutes les egliſes &amp; de toute l'a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſtration ſpiritnelle, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me ſcu ceſſeur de l'apoſtre S. Pierre: ioint que ceſte cité pour ſon an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cienne dignite &amp; grandeur, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenoit, comme de touts les au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3676:13"/>
le nom &amp; la maieſté de l'empire, &amp; que d'icelle la foy Chreſtienne auoit eſté eſpan due en la plus grande partie de l'Europe.</p>
            <p>Auſsi que l'empereur Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin aiant eſté baptizé par Sylueſtre, auoit uolontiers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congneu, &amp; comme approuué telle authorité, &amp; preeminence en luy &amp; ſes ſucceſſeurs.</p>
            <p>On dit dauantage, que Con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantin conſtraint pour les af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires des prouinces d'Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent de tranſporter le ſiege de l'Empire en la citó de Byzanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um appelléc depuis de ſon nom Conſtantinople, donna au pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe la ſeigneurie de Romme et de pluſieurs autres uilles &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions d'Italie: lequel bruit, bien qu il aye eſté entretenu diligem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment par les papes qui ſuccede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent, &amp; par leur authorité creu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de pluſieurs, toutefois eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouué par les autheurs plus dignes de foy, &amp; encor plus par l'eſtat des choſes meſmes:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3676:14"/>
d'au tant qu'il eſt treſcertain &amp; manifeſte que lors &amp; long te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ps depuis la uille de Romme, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble toute l'Italie, fut gouuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>née comme ſubiete à l'empire, uoire par officiers &amp; magiſtrats deputez par les empereurs.</p>
            <p>Encore y en a'il (tant eſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fonde ſouuentefois l'oſcurite<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es choſes ſi anciennes) qui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prenent &amp; refutent hardiment tout ce qu'il ſe dit de Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin &amp; de Sylueſtre, affermans qu'ilsont ueſcu en diuers temps</p>
            <p>Mais tous font d'accord que le tranſport du ſiege de l'Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire en la uille de Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, fut la ſource &amp; origine de la puiſſance des papes: par ce qu'affoibliſſans auec le temps l'authorité des Empereurs en Italie, pour leur continuelle ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence &amp; pour les gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds affaires qu'ils auoyent en l'Orient, le peuple Romain fe retirant de l'obeiſſance des empereurs &amp; d'autant plus deferant auz pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, commenca à leur preſter, non pas uraye ſubiection, mais vnecertaine obeiſſance volon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taire.</p>
            <p>Il eſt uray que ces choſes ne
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3676:15"/>
ſe manifeſterent ſinon lente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; peu a peu, pour les in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaſions des Gothz, Vandales &amp; autres nations barbares qui ſur uindrent en Italie: par leſquels eſtant la uille de Romme pluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eurs fois prinſe &amp; ſaccagée, le nom du pape demeura pour quelque temps fort obſcur &amp; abiect, &amp; l'authorité des empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reurs fort petite en Italie, d'au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant qu'auec telle ignominie ils la laiſſoyent en proye aux nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons barbares.</p>
            <p>Entre leſquelles ayant eſté l'enuahiſſement de toutes les autres comme un torrent, la pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſſance des Gothz, qui eſtoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent une gent de nom &amp; de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion Chreſtienne ſortie de ſa premiere origine des parties de Dace &amp; de Tartarie, ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinua par l'eſpace de ſoixante &amp; dix ans:</p>
            <p>Laquelle en fin eſtant dechaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſée par les armes des empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reurs, l'Italie commenca de nouueau à ſe gouuerner par
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3676:16"/>
magiſtrats Grecs: entre leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quels celuy qui eſtoit plus grand &amp; ſuperieur à tous les autres, appellé d'u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nom Grec Exarcha, faiſoit ſa reſidence à Rauenne, ville treſancienne &amp; lors moult riche &amp; moult peuplée, pour la fertilité du pays, pource auſsi que depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is le grand accroiſſement qu'elle receut par la puiſſance armée de mer qu'Auguſte Ceſar &amp; les autres Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reurs entretenoient continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellement au port qui eſtoit aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſez proche de la uille, (duquel toutefois il ne reſte auiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'huy apparence aucune) elle auoit eſté habitee de plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs capitaines &amp; chefs de guerre, &amp; depuis par un long temps de Theodoric roy des Goths &amp; de ſes ſucceſſeurs, leſquels redoutans encor la puiſſance des empereurs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyent pluſtoſt esleuceſte vil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le-la pour aſſiette de leur roy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aume que Romme, pour la commodité de la mer qui eſt plus prochaine de Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinoble.</p>
            <p>Pour la quelle commodité
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3676:17"/>
(bien que pour raiſon toute contraire) les Exarches ſ'y e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans arreſtez, ils deputerent au gouuernement de Romme &amp; des autres citez d'Italie des ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrats particuliers ſous le til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre de ducs.</p>
            <p>De la eut ſon origine le nom de l'Exarchat de Rauenne, ſous lequel eſtoyt comprins tout ce qui n'ayant un duc particulier obeiſſoit immediatement à l'Exarche.</p>
            <p>En ce temps les papes de Romme priuez de toute puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance temporelle, eſtant la re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence ſpirituelle qu'on leur portoit auprecedent comme abbaſtardie &amp; anea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie par la diſſimulation de leurs bonnes couſtumes qui commencoient deſia à ſe paſſer, eſtoyent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſubiects aux Empereurs: ſans la confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delquels ou de leur Exarche, bien quils fuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent esleus par le clergé &amp; peu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple de Romme, ils n'oſoient ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepter ou exercer leur pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3676:18"/>
aincois, dautant que com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munement le ſiege de la religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enſuit la puiſſance de l'Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire &amp; des armes, les Eueſques de Conſtantinoble &amp; de Rauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne diſputoyent: ſouuentefois de la ſuperiorité auec l'eueſque de Rome.</p>
            <p>Mais peu de temps apres l'e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtat des choſes ſe changea. Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les Lombards (gent fort cruel le) eſtans entrez en Italie, occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perent la Gaule ciſalpine (la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quelle de leur empire print le nom de Lombardie) Rauenne auec tout l'Exarchat &amp; plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs autres parties d'Italie, &amp; eſtendirent leurs armes inſqu'a la marque d'Ancoue, Spolete &amp; Beneuent, eſquels deux lieux ils creerent &amp; eſtablirent Ducs particuliers.</p>
            <p>A quoy cependant les empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reurs ne donnant aucun ordre, partie pour leut couardiſe &amp; nonchal lance, partie pour les
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3676:19"/>
difficultés &amp; empeſchemens qui'ls auoient lors du coſtéd A ſie, la uille de Romme eſtant de ſtituée de leur ſecours n'y ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant plus en Italie de magiſtrat des Exarches, commenca à ſe gouuerner par le conſeil &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorité des papes: leſquels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puis vn ſi long temps eſtans auec les Romaines oppreſſez par les Lombards, eurent fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalement recours à l'aide de Pepin roy de France, lequel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant paſſé en Italie auec vne puiſſant'armée dechaſſade ceſt Empire vne partie des Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards qui y auoientia dominé plus de deux cens ans, &amp; don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na au pape &amp; à l'Egliſe de Rom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, comme choſes deuenues ſiennes par droict de guerre, non ſeulement Vrbino, Fano, Eugupio &amp; pluſieurs terres pro chaines de Romme, mais auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Rauenne auec ſon Exarchat, ſous lequel on dit qu'eſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prins tout ce qui eſt depuis les confins de Plaiſance, contiguz au territoire de Pauie iuſques
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3676:20"/>
à Arimini, entre le fleuue du Pau &amp; l'Apennin, les eſtangs, ou pluſtoſt marets &amp; palus des Venetiens &amp; la mer Adriatque &amp; depuis Arimini iuſqu'au fleu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue de la Toglia, lequel lors on appeloit Iſaurum.</p>
            <p>Mais apres la mort de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin, eſtant aduenu que les Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards troubloient de nouueau le pape &amp; ce qui luy auoit eſté donné, Charles fils de Pepin (apres que pour ſes grandes proueſſes &amp; victoires, il fut à bon droict appellé Le grand) aiant deſtruit entierement leur empire, conferma la donation faicte parſon pere à l'egliſe de Rome, &amp; approuua ce, que pen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dant qu'il guerroioit les Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards la marque d'Ancone &amp; la duché de Spolete (laquelle comprenoit la cité d'Aquila &amp; vne partie de la Brutie) s eſtoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent volonterement données
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3676:21"/>
au pape. On afferme ce que ie i'ay dit pour tout certain.</p>
            <p>A quoy aucuns eſcriuains ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſtiques adiouſtent encor que Charles donna à l'egliſe le Ligurie iuſqu'au fleuue de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, dernier confin d Italie, Man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toue, &amp; tout ce que les Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards poſſedoient en Friuoli &amp; en'Hiſtrie.</p>
            <p>Quelqu'un auſsi eſcrit le meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me de I'Ile de Corſe &amp; de tout le territoire qui eſt contenu en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre les villes de Luna &amp; de Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</p>
            <p>Pour lequel bienfaict les rois de France celebrez &amp; eſleuez parles papes, acquirent le tiltre de Rois Treschreſtiens. Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is &amp; enuiron l'an de grace huict cens, le pape Leon &amp; le peu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple de Romme (le Pape, di-ie, ſans autre puiſſance ou autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rité que de chef de ce peuple) eſleurent ce meſme Charles pour Empereur de Romme, ſeparans meſmes pat ce nom ceſte partie de l'Empire de ceux
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3676:22"/>
qui habitoient à Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: comme ſi Romme &amp; les prouinces de l'Occident n'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans deffendues par eux, euſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteu beſoin d'eſtre deffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues &amp; gardées par vn prince qui leur fuſt comme propre, &amp; particulier.</p>
            <p>Par la quelle diuiſion les Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereurs de Conſtantinoble ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>furent encor priuez de la Sici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le, ne de la partie d'Italie, laquel le tirant deuers Naples à Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredoni, eſt bornée de la mer, d'autant qu'elles eſtoyent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourées continuellement ſous la puiſſance de leurs Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reurs.</p>
            <p>Cependant par tout cela ne fut derogué à la couſtume, ſuiuant laquelle l'election du pape ſe confermoit par l'Empereur Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>main, ſous le nom duquel ſe gouuernoit la ville de Romme: ains les papes meſmes par leurs bulles, priuileges &amp; conceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, quottoient le temps par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces paroles expreſſes &amp; formel les: IMPERANTE CARO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LO IMP. DOMINO NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRO. En laquelle ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3676:23"/>
ou recognoiſſance ils conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuerent iuſques à ce, non pas que le ſuccez des affaires leur donnaſt courage de ſe gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner par ſoymeſmes, mais qu'ai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ant la puiſſance de ces Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reurs commencé de s'affoibler premierement par les conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions qui ſuruindrent entre les ſucceſſeurs meſmes de Charle maigne, pendant que la dignité imperiale demoura entre leurs mains, puis par eſtre tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tée à des princes Allemans, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quels n'eſtoient ſi puiſſans que ceux de la lignée de Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne, pour la grandeur du roiaume de France, &amp; le pape &amp; le peuple de Romme &amp; le ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrat, par lequella uille, bien que tumultueuſement, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menca d'eſtre gouuernée, en de rogeant entierement en tout ce qui leur eſtoit posſible à la iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſdiction des empereurs, ordo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerent par un decret &amp; loy ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennelle, que des lors en auaut l'election du pape n'auroit que
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3676:24"/>
faire d'eſtre confermée par l'em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereur.</p>
            <p>Ce qui s'obſerua diuerſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t par un long temps, ſelon que la puiſſance des empereurs ſe le uoit ou s'abaiſſoit par diuers ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cez des affaires: laquelle eſtant grandement accreue depuis que l'Empire fut uenu entre les mains des Othons de Saxe, le pape eſleu par la faueur d'Otho le tiers lors preſent, meu d'affec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion &amp; amour particulier en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſa propre nation, &amp; irrité du mauuais traictement qu'il auoit reeeu du peuple Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, tranſporta par ſon ordon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance aux Allemans la puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance d'elire, l'empereur de Romme en la forme &amp; maniere qui s'obſerue encor de noſtre temps: deffendant toutefois à ceux qui ſeroient eſleus (pour reſeruer touſiours aux Papes quelque preeminence) de n'u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3676:25"/>
du tiltre d'Empereur ou Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſte ſinon que premierement ils euſſent receu la couronne de l'Empire.</p>
            <p>Dont eſt procedée la cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume de venir à Romme pour ſe faire couronner, &amp; de ne s'at tribuer auparauant autre tiltre que de Roy des Rommains &amp; de Ceſar.</p>
            <p>Mais eſtans depuis les Othons deffaillis &amp; la puiſſance des em pereurs amoindrie, d'autant que l'Empire ne ſe continuoit hereditairement en rois grands &amp; puiſſants, la ville de Romme ſe retira ouuertement de leur obeiſſance, &amp; ſe rebellerent plu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſieurs citez au temps de l'Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hereur Conrad de Sueue, pen dant que les Papes, entendans touſiours à ſ'aggrandir de plus en plus, ſeigneurioient preſque entierement la ville de Rome, combien que ſouuentes fois par l'inſolence &amp; diſcorde du peuple ils euſſent bcaucoup d'affaires.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3676:26"/>Pour auſquels obuier, ils a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyent ia par la faueur de l'Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereur Henri ſecond, qui lors eſtoit à Romme, tranſporté aux cardinaux ſeuls, par loy &amp; ordo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance ſolennelle, la puiſſance &amp; authorité d'eſlire &amp; creer le Pape. Auquel lors encor ſe pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenta vn nouueau moien de s'aggrandir.</p>
            <p>Carenuiron ce temps ayant les Northmans (deſquels le pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mier fut Guillaume ſurnomme Brasdeſer) vſurpé ſur l'Empire de Conſtantinoble l'Apouille &amp; la Calabre, Robert Guiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard l'un d'eux, ou pour ſe pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ualoir daua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage auec ceſte cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leur &amp; apparence de quelque droict, ou pour ſe rendre plus puiſſant à ſe deffendre contre les Empereurs, ou pour autre occaſion, rendit Beneuent au Pape, comme eſtant des appar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenances de l'Egliſe Romaine, &amp; reprint d'el le en fief le duché
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3676:27"/>
del Apouille &amp; de Calabre. Le quel exemple fut enſuiui par Roger l un de ſes ſucceſſeurs, lequel ayant dechaſsé de la Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille &amp; de la Calabre Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laume de la meſme famille, &amp; depuis occupé la Sicile, euuiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> l'an mil cent trente, recong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neut ces meſmes pays comme mouuans en fief de l'Egliſe, en qualite de roy des deux Siciles, l'une delà, l'autre decà le Far: le Pape cependant ne refuſaut pas de fauoriſer, pour ſon ambi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion &amp; prouffit particulier, l'u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation &amp; la violence de ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuy cy.</p>
            <p>Auec tous ces moyens les papes croiſſants touſiours de plus en plus en puiſſance &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite (comme iamais la con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoitiſe des hommes ne s'aſſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit) ils commencerent de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer de ces royaumes les Roys qui n'obeiſſoient à leurs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemens, &amp; les tranſporter &amp; conferer à autres: iuſques à ce qu'ils paruindrent à Hedry fils de Frederic Barberouſſe, &amp;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3676:28"/>
de Henry à Frideric ſecond ſon fils, tous trois ſucceſſiuement Empereurs.</p>
            <p>Mais eſtant Frideric deuenu grand perſecuteur de l'Egliſe, &amp; s'eſtant de ſon temps eſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uees les factions des Guelpes &amp; des Gibellins, (de l'une deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quelles les Papes eſtoit chef, &amp; de l'antre l'Empereur) apres la mort de Frideric, le Pape confera l'inueſtiture de ces roy aumes à Charles Conte d'An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iou, &amp; de Prouence, duquel à eſté faicte mention cy deſſus, à la charge de ſix mil onces d'or de cens par chaſcun an, &amp; que aucuns de ces rois ne peuſſent à l'aduenir eſtre Empereurs de Romme: Laquelle condition à touſiours depuis eſté ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiée ences inueſtitures.</p>
            <p>Et pour ceſte occaſion le roy aume de l'iſle de Sicile ſe retira
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3676:29"/>
peu apres de l'obeiſance de l'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſe, quant au cens &amp; á la re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congnoiſſance feudale. Encor le bruit commun a gaigné ce poinct (bien qu'il ne ſoit du tout ſi certain que ce que nous auo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ia dit cy deſſus) que long te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ps au parauant la Conteſſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haut, princeſſe tres puiſſante en Italie, donna à l'Egliſe ceſte par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie de la Toſcane, laquelle bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>née du torrent de Peſera du cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteau de S. Quirico &amp; de la riui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre du Tybre, s'appelle au iour d'huy le Parrimoine de ſainct Pierre. Et adiouſtent encor au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuns que la cite de Ferrare fut paraillement donnée à l'Egliſe par ceſte meſme conteſſe. Ces dernieres choſes ne ſont bien aſſeurees, mais encor eſt plus douteux ce qui a eſte eſcrit par aucuns, qu' Arithpert roy des Lombards, lors que leur regne floriſſoit, luy donna les Alpes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3676:30"/>
appellees Cotties, eſquelles on dit auſsi que Gennes eſt enclos enſemble tout ce qui eſt conte nu depuis Gennes iuſqu'aux confins de la Prouence: Et que Linthprandus, auſsi roy de la meſme nation, luy donna la Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, pais proche de Romme, Narni, Ancone, auec certaines autres terres.</p>
            <p>Ainſi ſelon la varieté de l'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat des Empereurs varierent auſsi les affaires des papes auec eux.</p>
            <p>Car aiants au commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſté longuement perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tez par ces Empereurs, &amp; depu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>is deliurez de ceſte crainte par la conuerſion de Conſtantin, ils ſe repoſerent auſsi longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſous l'ombre de leurs ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, s'emploiants ſeulement aux choſes ſpirituelles veſquirent et par vne longue eſpace de temps en bas eſtat, ſeparez to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talement du commerce des em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereurs pour la puiſſance des Lombards en Italie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3676:31"/>Mais depuis eſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s paruenus par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le benefice du roy de France, aux principautez et ſeigneuries temporelles, ils demourerent grandement vnis auec les em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereurs, dependans fort volon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers de leur authorité cepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant que la dignité d'empereur ſe continua en la lignee de Charlmaigne, tant pour la ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenance des bie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-faicts recipro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quement receus &amp; donnez, que pour le reſpect de la grandeur Imperialle: laquelle depuis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t á decliner, s'eſtants du tout ſeparez de leur amitié, ils com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencerent à faire profeſsion &amp; maintenir que c'eſtoit pluſtoſt au Pape de donner la loy à l'em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereur que de la receuoir de luy.</p>
            <p>Ainſi ayants en horreur ſur toutes choſes de retourner en leur ancienne ſubiection, &amp; à ce que les Empereurs n'entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prinſſent de recognoiſtre à Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; ailleurs les anciens droicts de l'Empire (comme
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3676:32"/>
aucuus d'eux eſtans ou plus pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſſans, ou d'un eſprit plus haut &amp; courageux s'efforcoient de faire) ils s'oppoſoient à deſcou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uert auec armes à leur puiſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce accompagnez de ces tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, leſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quels ſous un nom de prince, &amp; des citez qui s'eſtoient aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies &amp; miſes en liberté, ne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congnoiſſoient plus l'authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té de l Empire.</p>
            <p>De là vint que les Papes, s'at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tribuants dauantage de iour à autre, &amp; conuertiſſans la ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reur des armes ſpirituelles aux choſes temporelles, (faiſans ceſte interpretation que com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vicaires de Chriſt en terre ils eſtoient ſuperieurs à l'Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reur, &amp; qu'a eux en pluſieurs cas appartenoit le ſoin de l'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat de ce monde) priuoient quelques fois les Empereurs de leur dignité imperiale, ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tants les electeurs à en eſlire d'autres au lieu dez excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niez, &amp; de autre coſté les Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reurs
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3676:33"/>
ou eſliſoient eux meſmes ou procuroient l'election de nouueaux papes.</p>
            <p>De ces contentions aduint qu'eſtant l'eſtat de l'Egliſe fort affoibli tant par la demeure de la court de Romme par l'e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpace de ſoixante &amp; dix ans en la ville d'Auignon, que par le ſchiſme qui ſucceda au retour du Pape en Italie, qu'és villes ſubiettes à l'Egliſe, &amp; principal leme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t en celles de la Romaigne pluſieuis puiſſans citadins oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuperent la tyranny en leur pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pre pais, leſquels depuis les pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes dechaſſerent, ou n'eſtans aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſez puiſſans pour les debuter, accorderent ces ſeigneuries en fief ou à ceuxmeſmes qui les auoient occupées, ou à au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres chefs qu'ils ſubſtituoient contre eux. Ainſi commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent les villes de la Romaigne à auoir ſeigneurs particuliers la plus part ſous tiltre des vicaires del Egliſe.</p>
            <p>Ainſi Ferrare bailée au com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mencement en gouuernement
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3676:34"/>
à Azo d'Aeſt, luy fut depuis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedée en tiltre de vicariat, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uec le temps fut ceſte famille eſleuée en tiltres plus grands &amp; illuſtres.</p>
            <p>Ainſi Boloigne occupée par Iean Viſconte archeueſque de Millan, luy fut depuis ac cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee en Vicariat par le pape: &amp; pour les meſmes occaſions en pluſieurs terres de la marque d'Ancone, du Patrimoine S. Pierre &amp; de l'Vmbrie (qu'on appelle maintenant la Duché de Spolete) s'eſleuerent pluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eurs ſeigneurs particuliers, ou contre la volonté du pape, ou de ſon conſentement forcé.</p>
            <p>Leſquels changemens eſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſemblablement ſuruenus en la Lombardie és citez de l'Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, il aduint telles fois, ſelon la varieté des affaires, que les Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caires de la Romaigne &amp; des autres terres eccleſiaſtiques ſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3676:35"/>
retirans ouuertement du nom de l'Egliſe, recognoiſſoient ces citez en fief de l'Empereur: comme au contraire, ceux qui occupoient en Lombardie Millan, Mantoue, &amp; autres ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res imperiales, les recongnoiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoient en fief du pape.</p>
            <p>En ce temps, bien que la vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le de Romme retint le nom &amp; la ſeigneury de l'egliſe, touie fois elle ſe gouuernoit ſoy meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Et ores qu'au commence<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment que les papes retourne rent d'Auignon, ils fuſſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beis comme ſeigneurs, cenea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t moins peu apres les Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mains aians creé le magiſtrat de Ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derez, retournerent à leur anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enne contumace.</p>
            <p>Parquoy n'eſtant demou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>é aux papes que bien peu de pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſance, ils commencerent à ſe retirer de ceſte ville, &amp; n'y fire<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t plus de demourance, iuſqu'a ce que les Romains appauuris,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3676:36"/>
eſtans auſsi tombez en treſgra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deſordre pour l'abſence de la court, voiant que l'anee mil quatre cens eſtoit proche, en la quelle ils eſperoient que le pape eſtant en la ville de Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me il y auroit grande affluence de gens de toutes parts de la Chreſtienté pour raiſon du Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile, ils ſupplierent treshum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blement Boniface qu'il luy pleuſt y retourner, offrans de caſſer incontinent leurs Bande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rez, &amp; de ſe ſousmettre entiere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment à ſon obeiſſance.</p>
            <p>Sous leſquelles conditions eſtant le Pape retourné à Rom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, pendant que les citoyens s'amuſoient entierement au gain de ceſte annce, il print ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluement la ſeigneurie de la ville, fortifia &amp; mit gardes au chaſtel ſainct Ange, tellement que ſes ſucceſſeurs iuſqu'au pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe Eugene, bien qu'ils euſſent ſouuentefois beaucoup de dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultez, aiant ce neantmoins eſtabli en fin leur puiſſance, les ſeigneurierent depuis ſans au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cune contradiction.</p>
            <p>Auec ces fondemens &amp; moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3676:37"/>
eſtans eleuez en grande pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſſance terrienne, delaiſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s peu à peu la memoire du ſalut des ames &amp; des commandemens de Dieu, ayants tourné toutes leurs penſees à la grandeur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce monde, n'uſants plus de l'au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thorité ſpirituelle ſi non pour u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtrument &amp; miniſtere de la temporelle, ils commencerent à ſembler pluſtoſt princes ſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liers que papes ou eueſques.</p>
            <p>Leur ſoin &amp; leur affaires commencerent lors d'eſtre, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plus l'aduancement de la religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, non plus lezele &amp; la chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té enuers leprochain, mais les armes, mais les guerres contre contre les Chreſtiens: &amp; cepen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dant de manier auec leurs pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees &amp; mains ſanguinaires les ſacrifices, amaſſer des threſors: nouelles loix, noueaux artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nouuelles trahiſons, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueaux pieges pour atraper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers de tous coſtez: employer à ceſte fin ſans aucun reſpect les armes ſpirituelles, vendre ſans honte &amp; vergongne les choſes ſacrees &amp; prophanes.</p>
            <p>Depuis les richeſſes eſtans eſpandues en toute leur court
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3676:38"/>
s'en enſuyuirent les pompes &amp; desbordemens, les facons de faire deshoneſtes, les voluptez &amp; plaiſirs abominables: nul ſoin de leurs predeceſſeurs, nul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le penſee de la maieſté perpetu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>elle de leur pontificat: mais au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieu de cela, des deſirs ambiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eux &amp; peſtiferez d'eſleuer, non ſeulement à richeſſes exorbita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, mais à roiaumes &amp; princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pautez leurs fils, leurs nepueux &amp; leurs parens: ne diſtribuans plus les dignitez ny les prouf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits &amp; reuenus aux hommes dignes &amp; vertueux, mais preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que touſiours les vendans aux plus offrans, ou les diſsipans en perſonnes propres à leur ambi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, auarice, ou à leurs plaiſirs vilains &amp; deteſtables.</p>
            <p>Pour raiſon deſquels actes eſtant la reuerence qu'on leur portoit du tout perdue au coeur des hommes, toutefois leur authorité ſe ſouſtient en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor en partie pour le nom et la maieſté tant puiſſante de la reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion, eſtant cependant grande<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment aidee des moiens qu'ils ont de gratifier aux grands princes &amp; à ceux qui onr quel que puiſſance autour d'eux, par
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3676:39"/>
le moien des dignitez et autres concesſions eccleſiaſtiques.</p>
            <p>De la aduient que congnoiſ ſans bien qui'ls ſont en grand reſpect enuers les hommes, et que celuy qui prent les armes contre eux ne peut attendre qu'une grieue infamie auec li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitié des autres princes qui s'oppoſent ſouuentefois à tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les enterprinſes, et qu'en tout euenement il en recoit bien peu de gain: qu'eſtans vainec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urs ils exercent leur victoire à leur diſcretion, vaincus, ils en eſchappent à telles conditions que bon leur ſemble: eſtans ain ſi pouſſez &amp; eguillonnez d'un deſir et cupidité d'eſleuer leurs parents de bas lieu aux princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pautez, ils ont de long temps eſté par pluſieurs fois les inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments de guerres, &amp; feux nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueaux en Italie.</p>
            <p>Mais retournant à mon prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipal propos, duquel la treſ-iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte douleur du dommaige pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lic m'a plus ardemment tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porté que la loy de l'hiſtoire ne me permettoit, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="discourse">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3676:8"/>
            <head>A whole diſcourſe cleane <hi>left out of the fourth booke;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the <hi>119.</hi> pa. accor- to the ſaid impreſsion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the declaration whereof, and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye other thinges which happened af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, the matter requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth that I now make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what right the church hath ouer the territorie of <hi>Romagna,</hi> and many other places, which it hath hadde poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in diuers times, and holdeth yet at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: And by what meanes the biſhops of Rome, being appointed, and eſtabliſhed only for the pure, and ſimple adminiſtration of ſpirituall matters are nowe come to the managing of worldlie ſtates, and principalities: And likewiſe that I declare (as a matter conioyned heer vnto) what ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention hath hapned diuers times, thorow theſe, &amp; other occaſions, betweene the popes and the Emperors.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops of Rome (of whome S. Peter was the firſt) their power and autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3676:9"/>
in ſpirituall matters beeing grounded on Ieſus Chriſt, being men renowned for their Charitie, humility, patience, vnderſtanding, &amp; miracles, were at their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, not onely void of al temporal authoritie and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, but perſecuted by the ſame, and for a long time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained obſcure, and as it were men vnknowne, theyr name beeing for the moſte part manifeſt to the worlde, onelye by the tortures and afflictions they ſuffered, which they endured equally with them that ſucceeded them. For albeit that tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough the great concourſe of people, and the diuerſitie of Nations and profeſſions which were then at Rome, ſmall regard was taken to their proceedinges, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Emperors did not at all, mooue any force, or trouble againſt them, but when they were of opinion, that it was not meet to diſſemble theyr publike actions, or pas them ouer with ſilence: howbeit other Emperors, whether it were thorow crueltie, or for the loue they did beare to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3676:10"/>
their perticular gods, did perſecute them with all ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, as the authors of newe ſuperſtitions, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerters of true religion.</p>
            <p>In this eſtate they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, beeing highlie renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for their voluntarie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, holineſſe of life, and martirdome, vntill the time of pope <hi>Silueſter:</hi> in whoſe life the Emperor <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> being conuerted to the Chriſtian faith, and mooued by the holy conuerſation &amp; miracles, which were dailie manifeſted in thoſe, whoe made profeſſion of the name of Chriſt, the Biſhops were freed from the perſecution which they had endured the ſpace of three hundred years (or thereabout) and had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty granted them, publike<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie to exerciſe Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon through the reuerence to their holy life, &amp; the diuine precepts which our religion containeth: and through the readines which is ingrafted in men, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the example of their prince; whether it were (as it often falleth out) through
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3676:11"/>
ambicion, or fear: the name of Chriſtians, began woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully to encreaſe &amp; ſpread it ſelfe euerye where, and withall the pouertie of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: For <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing builte at Rome, the Churches of S. <hi>Iohn in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terano,</hi> of S. <hi>Peter in Vatica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> and of ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie others in diuers places, he did not only furniſh them with rich veſſels and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but moreouer enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them, with great poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and reuenues, that they might in time to come be maintained, and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that they which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed diuine ſeruice might liue thereby: Afterwardes by ſucceſſion, many perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues, that by almes, and guiftes to the church, they ſhoulde eaſilie purchaſe the kingdome of heauen, they either builte new churches, which they endowed with poſſeſſions, or bequeathed part of their riches, to thoſe which were alreadie founded and erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: yea whether it were by a law, or by an auncient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3676:12"/>
following the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the olde Teſtament, euerye one paide the tenth part of his fruites, and the reuenues of his own goods to the church: wherevnto they were ſtirred vppe and animated, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great feruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, becauſe at the firſt the Eccleſiaſtical perſons beſide that which ſerued for their moderate maintenance, did employ the reſt of their goods, in building and bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieng of the churches; O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles in pittifull and charitable deeds, pride, and ambition, being not yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into their harts, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for themſelues onelie that which ſuffiſed to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelues frugality, and with temperance.</p>
            <p>The biſhop of Rome, was then acknowledged general<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of al Chriſtians, ſuperior of the church and of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gouernment, as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of the Apoſtle Peter, both becauſe that cittie, for the dignitie and greatneſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3676:13"/>
thereof, did as chiefe heade of others retaine the name and maieſtie of the Empire, as alſo that from thence the chriſtian faith was diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thrugh the greater part of Europe: And further for that <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> beeing baptiſed by <hi>Silueſter,</hi> did free<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly yeelde that authoritye to him, and his ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, the report is, that <hi>Conſtantine</hi> beeing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the affaires of the Prouinces of the Eaſte partes, to remooue the ſeat of his Empire to <hi>Bizantium,</hi> which afterward hee called by his owne name <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> gaue to the Biſhop the gouernement of Rome, and of many other citties, and countreys of <hi>Italie:</hi> The which reporte albeit that with great aduiſe it was entertained by the Popes which did ſucceede, and by their aucthoritie beleeued of manie, notwithſtanding the ſame is reprooued by moſte approoued aucthors, and altogether refuted by the eſtate of matters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3676:14"/>
For it is moſte cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that at that time, and longe after, Rome and all <hi>Italie,</hi> was gouerned as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Empire, and that by Magiſtrates deputed by the Emperors. Moreouer there are many (matters of great antiquitie, are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo obſcured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> darke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes) whoe doe flatlie deny, all that is reported of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> and <hi>Sylueſter,</hi> affyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that they liued in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ages. But all doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the chaunging of the ſeate of the Empire to the cittye of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> was the firſt beginninge of the authority of the Popes: For the power of the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors growing weake in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> through their continuall abſence, and vrgent affaires which withhelde them in the eaſt partes, the people of <hi>Rome</hi> withdrawing them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues from the obedience of the Emperors, and ſo much the more leauing vnto the Popes, they began to yeelde vnto them, not anie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection indeed, but a certain kinde of voluntarie obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Albeit that theſe thinges
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3676:15"/>
were not broughte to light but by tract of time, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſlowlie, by reaſon of the inuaſion of the <hi>Gothes, Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals,</hi> and other Barbarous Nations, which came into <hi>Italie:</hi> by whome the cittye of Rome beeing taken and ſacked, manie times the names of the popes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning temporall matters, did remaine verye obſcure and baſe, and the authoritie of the Emperors very ſmal, forſomuch as they did with great diſhonor, leaue <hi>Italie,</hi> in pray to barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Amongſt whom the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of other Nations hauing been as the courſe of a migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie riuer, the power of the <hi>Gothes</hi> continued the ſpace of ſeuentie yeares:</p>
            <p>Theſe were chriſtians by name and profeſſion, and tooke their firſte beginning from the partes of <hi>Dacia,</hi> and <hi>Tartaria;</hi> who neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe in the end beeing driuen from <hi>Italie,</hi> by the armye of the Emperours, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries began againe to be go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3676:16"/>
by Magiſtrates of <hi>Greece:</hi> of the which he which hadde ſoueraigne authoritie ouer the reſte, beeing by a Greeke worde called <hi>Hexarche,</hi> did make his ordinarie reſidence in <hi>Rauenna</hi> a moſte auncient citty, and at that time ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry rich and populus: both in reſpect of the fertilitye of the countrey, as alſo by reaſon of the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thither, from the mightie armie at Sea, which <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> and other Emperors did conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuallie entertaine, in the hauen neer vnto the town (wherof at this day there remaineth not ſcarſe anie remembrance) it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited by manye capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and afterwards a long time by <hi>Theodoric</hi> K. of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, who yet ſtanding in dreade of the power of the Emperors, did rather make choice of this town for the ſeate of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then Rome, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the conueniencie of the Sea, beeing nearer to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In conſideration wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3676:17"/>
(albeit for a contrarie reaſon) the <hi>Hexarches</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſtabliſhed in <hi>Rauenna</hi> did depute or appoint, par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticular. Magiſtrates for the gouernment of Rome and other citties of <hi>Italie,</hi> vnder the title of Dukes. From hence the name of <hi>Hexarchie</hi> of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> did grow, vnder which title al that was comprehended, which hauing no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Duke, did immediatlie obey the <hi>Hexarchie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this time the biſhop of Rome, exerciſing no ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill authoritie, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence in ſpirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which before men did bear vnto them, in reſpect of their holineſſe of life (which now they made no ſhew of) declining and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, they liued as ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect to the Emperours: without whoſe approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the conſent of their <hi>Hexarches,</hi> albeit choice were made by the Clergie and people of Rome, yet durſt they not accept of or exerciſe the place of bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3676:18"/>
Moreouer, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> &amp; <hi>Rauenna</hi> (as commonly the ſeate of Religion, doth fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low the power of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and force of armes) did often diſpute with the Biſhoppes of Rome for ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perioritie.</p>
            <p>But not long after, the ſtate of matters didde change: for the <hi>Lombards</hi> (a verie cruell people) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred into Italie, did poſſeſſe that part of <hi>Gaul,</hi> which is called <hi>Ciſalpina</hi> (which from their gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment tooke the name of <hi>Lombardy) Rauenna,</hi> with the whole <hi>Hexarchie,</hi> and many other towns of <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</hi> and extended their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to the <hi>Marque</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cona, Spoleto,</hi> and <hi>Beneuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to,</hi> in which twoe places they did eſtabliſh particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Dukes.</p>
            <p>In the mean ſeaſon the Emperours not looking to theſe matters, partlie thorow their cowardiſe &amp; negligence, and partly tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3676:19"/>
the lets and broiles they had in the coaſt of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, the cittie of Rome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and the gouernment of the <hi>Hexarches</hi> beeing worne out of Italie, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to bee ruled by the counſell and authoritie of the Biſhops: who hauing a longe time (together with the Romaines) been oppreſſed by the <hi>Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bardes,</hi> in the ende had recourſe vnto <hi>Pepin</hi> king of <hi>France</hi> for ſuccour, whoe paſſing into <hi>Italie</hi> with a mightie army, draue the greateſt parte of the <hi>Lombardes</hi> (who had ruled more than two hundred years) from their gouernement, and gaue vnto the pope and to the church of Rome, (as thinges fallen vnto him by right of Armes) not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie <hi>Vrbino, Fano, Agobbo,</hi> and many other territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries neere vnto Rome, but likewiſe <hi>Rauenna,</hi> with the <hi>Hexarchie</hi> thereof, vnder which title (they ſaye) is included, al that which is contained from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Placentia,</hi> ioyning to the Territorie of <hi>Pauia</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3676:20"/>
vnto <hi>Arimini,</hi> betweene the riuer <hi>Po,</hi> the mounte <hi>Apenine,</hi> the lake or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Venice,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique</hi> ſea: and from <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> vnto the riuer of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia,</hi> which at that time was called <hi>Iſaurum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after the death of <hi>Pepin,</hi> the <hi>Lombardes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing newe broiles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope, and thoſe poſſeſſions which were gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen him, <hi>Charles</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Pepin</hi> (who afterward for his worthy proweſſe, and many victories, was by right honoured with the name of Great) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vtterlie ſubuerted and brought their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to ruine, did confirm the guift made by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Church of Rome, and did giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and allowe of, that thoſe of the <hi>Marque</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cona,</hi> and the Duchie of <hi>Spoleto</hi> (which compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the cittie of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la,</hi> and a part of <hi>Brutia</hi>) did voluntarilie yeelde vnto the pope, whileſt he made
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3676:21"/>
wars with the <hi>Lombards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things they doe affirme as moſt certaine, to the which moreouer ſome Eccleſiaſticall Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters doe add, that <hi>Charles</hi> gaue to the church <hi>Liguria</hi> which extendeth to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Varo</hi> (the furtheſt ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of <hi>Italie) Mantua,</hi> and all that the <hi>Lombardes</hi> did poſſeſſe in <hi>Friuoli,</hi> and in <hi>Hiſtria.</hi> A certaine author writeth as muche of the Iſle of <hi>Corſica,</hi> and all the Territories which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, between the towns of <hi>Luna</hi> and <hi>Parma.</hi> For which ſo great benefites, the kinges of France bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing renowmed and honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red by the Popes, did pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to themſelues the ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Moſt chriſtian kinges:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And afterward in the yeer of Grace eight hundred, Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> together with the people of Rome (the Pope I ſay without anye other authoritie, as head of that people) didde chooſe <hi>Charles</hi> Emperor of the Romaines, diſtinguiſhing by that name, that parte of the Empire, from them
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3676:22"/>
which inhabited <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nople,</hi> as if Rome and the Weſt prouinces for want of ſuccour, were conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bee defended by a prince proper, and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to themſelues.</p>
            <p>Howbeit notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this deuiſion of the Empire, the emperours of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> were not diſpoſſeſſed, neyther of the Iſle of <hi>Sicilie,</hi> nor of that part of <hi>Italie,</hi> which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from <hi>Naples</hi> to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fredon,</hi> is encloſed with the Sea, the ſame beeing con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuallie vnder theyr go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, for all theſe accidents, the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was not abrogated but that the election of the pope muſt be allowed off, and confirmed by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Emperors, vnder whoſe name the Cittye of Rome was gouerned: nay further in their Buls and Charters, they did expres with theſe formal words, the time of the writing of them <hi>Imperante Carolo Imp. Domino noſtro.</hi> In
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3676:23"/>
which ſubiection or ackno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledgement they continued vntill the ſucceſſe of the af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faires did giue them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, to gouerne by themſelues.</p>
            <p>For when the power of the Emperours began to waxe weake, firſt thorowe the diſſention amongſt the ſucceſſours of <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> whileſt the maieſtie of the empire remained in their handes: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes by the change and remouing of the Empire, to the princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> whoe were not of like po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the ſucceſſours of <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the mightines of the houſe of France, both the Pope and the people of Rome, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates by whom the citty beganne to bee gouerned (though very diſorderlie) derogating wholy aſmuch as in them laye, from the iuriſdiction of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, they did ordaine by a ſolemne lawe and decree, that from thence forward
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3676:24"/>
the election of the pope, ſhoulde not depende of the authoritie of the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: which yet was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſlye obſerued a longe while after, according as the greatneſſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours by the ſucceſſe of matters did eyther riſe, or fall: And their power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatly increaſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the Empire came into the handes of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos</hi> of <hi>Saxony, Gregorye</hi> the fifth, by birth a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine beeing made pope, through the fauour of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho</hi> the thirde, whoe then was in Rome, partly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the loue of his owne Nation, and partlie prouoked by the iniuryes he receaued of the people of Rome, by his decree, tranſported the right and authority of chooſinge the Emperours, in the ſame forme they doe yet obſerue it at this day, to the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, and to the ende the Biſhoppes might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies reſerue ſome prehe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minence to themſelues, he did forbidde in his decree, that they which were to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3676:25"/>
bee choſen Emperours, might not vſe the title of emperor or <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> nor any other name, then king of the <hi>Romains,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> before they had receiued the Crowne of the empire from the pope, whence the cuſtome is growne that they come to Rome to bee crowned.</p>
            <p>But the houſe of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos</hi> being cleane extingui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed, and the power of the Emperors growne weak, by reaſon that the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof, did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the ſtocke of migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie and puiſſant kings, the citty of Rome did openlie withdrawe it ſelfe, from their obedience, and many other citties did rebell, in the reigne of the emperor <hi>Conrad</hi> of <hi>Sueuia:</hi> whileſt that the Biſhops ſtill ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding all their care by litle and litle, to aduance their owne greatneſſe, didde in a manner abſolutelie commande, and gouerne the Citty of Rome, albeit that oftentimes, by the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolency &amp; diſſention of the people, they had theyr
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3676:26"/>
handes full of buſineſſe: which that they might the better withſtand, thorowe the fauour of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cond being then at Rome; they obtained by a ſolemn lawe and decree, that the power and authority to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and create the Pope, ſhould remaine wholie in the cardinals.</p>
            <p>And to helpe this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a new meanes to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their greatneſſe offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelfe: For about that time the <hi>Northmans</hi> (of whom the firſt leader was <hi>William</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Iron-arme)</hi> hauing vſurped ouer the empire of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, Puglia,</hi> and <hi>Calabria: Robert Guicciard,</hi> one of the <hi>Northmans,</hi> whether it were that he might get the more aduantage, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a colour and pretence of right, or to arme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with greater force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the power of the emperors, or whether any other cauſe did leade him therevnto, he yeelded <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uent</hi> vnto the Pope, as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertaining to the churche of Rome, and helde of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3676:27"/>
ſaide church as in fee, the Dutchie of <hi>Apoullia,</hi> and <hi>Callabria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The which example <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger</hi> (one of his ſucceſſors) did followe, whoe hauing driuen <hi>William</hi> (diſcended of the ſame line) from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poullia</hi> and <hi>Callabria,</hi> and afterwards occupied <hi>Cici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia,</hi> about the yeare 1130. he helde likewiſe the ſaide countries, as in Fee of the church of Rome, vnder the title of the K. of both <hi>Sicilias,</hi> the one, on the one ſide, the other on the other ſide the <hi>Far:</hi> the popes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenting thorow their own ambition and particular profit, to nouriſh the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and vſurpation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>By all theſe means, the power and aucthoritie of the pope daily encreaſing (as the couetouſneſſe of men is neuer ſatiſfied) they did begin to depriue ſuch kinges of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, who were not obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dient to their commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to beſtowe the ſame vpon others: vntill the time that thoſe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3676:28"/>
fel into the houſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſonn of <hi>Frederic Barbarouſſa,</hi> and from <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry</hi> to <hi>Frederic</hi> the ſeconde his ſonne, al three of them beeing Emperours ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiuelie the one after the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Frederic</hi> being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a great perſecutour of the church, and in his time the faction of the <hi>Guelphes</hi> and <hi>Gibellins</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing growne (the Pope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing head of the one, &amp; the Emperour of the other) after the death of <hi>Frederic</hi> the pope inueſted <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Aniou</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence</hi> (of whome mention hath beene made heereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to thoſe kingdomes, vppon conditions to paye 6000. ounces of golde for tribute euery yeare, and that no king of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions might hereafter take vpon him the title of the Emperour of Rome: which condition hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince beene ſpecified, in the Charters of the kinge of <hi>Naples,</hi> which was the cauſe, that the kingdome of the Iſle of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> being
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3676:29"/>
poſſeſſed by the king of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> did withdraw it ſelf from the yearly tribute, &amp; from the acknoledgement to hold in fee of the church of Rome.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, report hath gotten thus muche (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be not ſo certain as thoſe thinges we haue diſcourſed of before) that long agoe the Counteſſe <hi>Mahaulte,</hi> a moſte mightie princeſſe in <hi>Italie,</hi> gaue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church that part of <hi>Toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane,</hi> which on the one ſide is limitted with the riuer <hi>Peſcia,</hi> and the caſtle of S. <hi>Querico</hi> in the earldom of <hi>Siena,</hi> &amp; on the other ſide with the lower ſea and the riuer <hi>Tiber,</hi> and is at this day called the patrimonie of S. <hi>Peter:</hi> Others adde that the ſaide counteſſe, gaue vnto the churche the citty of <hi>Ferrara.</hi> Theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thinges are not verie certaine, but farre more doutfull are thoſe matters which are written by a certain author, that <hi>Arith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pert</hi> king of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> when their kingdome did floriſh, did giue vnto them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3676:30"/>
the <hi>Alpes</hi> called <hi>Cocciae,</hi> wherein the cittie of <hi>Geno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua</hi> ſtandeth, and all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is contained, from <hi>Genoua</hi> vnto the borders of <hi>Prouence:</hi> And that <hi>Linthprandus</hi> likewiſe (K. of the ſame Nation) gaue vnto them <hi>Sabina,</hi> a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try neere vnto Rome, <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni,</hi> and <hi>Ancona,</hi> with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other territories.</p>
            <p>Thus according to the change and alteration of the Emperors, the affairs of the popes chaunged with them. For they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at the beginning byn many yeares perſecuted by the Emperors, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards freed from that feare, by the conuerſion of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they did a long while reſt in quyet, vnder the ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowe of their winges, and giuing themſelues wholie to ſpirituall matters, did liue in baſe eſtate, ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from the entercourſe they had with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, by reaſon of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the <hi>Lombards</hi> in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3676:31"/>But afterwards by the fauour of the K. of France being ſtepped vppe to tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porall authority, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned for a long ſpace, in league and amitye with the Emperors, depending verie willingly of their au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie, ſo long as the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie of the empire conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the ſtocke of <hi>Charls y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great,</hi> aſwell in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, giuen and receiued on both partes, as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the greatneſſe of the emperors which after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes comming to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline, the popes withdraw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing themſelues wholye from their friendſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to hold and maintaine that it belonged rather to them to giue lawes to the emperors, then to receiue lawes from them.</p>
            <p>Thus they diſdaining to enter into their former ſubiection, and to the ende that the emperors might not enterpriſe the recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the auncient right belonging to the empire, both at Rome and other places (as ſome of them be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3676:32"/>
either of greater pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, or more witte and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage then the reſt, endeuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red) they didde openlie by force of arms oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to their might, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſted by theſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants whoe (vnder the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and name of princes, &amp; of thoſe Citties, which did enfranchiſe, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues at libertie, they did no longer acknowledge &amp; ſubmit themſelues, to the authoritie of the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.</p>
            <p>Herevpon it came to pas that the popes taking dai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly more and more vppon them, and conuerting the terror of ſpirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to things temporall and enterpreting that as Chriſt his vicars on earth they hadde the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and place ouer em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, and that to them in certaine cauſes apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the care of the eſtate of this worlde, they did manye times depriue the emperors of their Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>periall dignitie, moouing the electors to chuſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the place of thoſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3676:33"/>
whom they had excommu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicated, and on the other ſide, the emperors did ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelues make choiſe of, or procure others to create new popes.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of theſe broils it hapned, that the eſtate of the church being great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly weakened, aſwell in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde that the Courte of Rome remained by the ſpace of 70. yeares in the citty of <hi>Auignon,</hi> as alſo thorow the ſchiſme which followed immediatlie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the pope his returne into <hi>Italy:</hi> and likewiſe, that in the citties which were ſubiect to the church and principallie in thoſe of <hi>Romagna,</hi> many cittizens who were of the greateſt power, did in their owne countrey vſurpe a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall gouernement whoe were eyther afterwards, forced from thence by the popes, or elſe (where they were not of power to ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe them) they did yeeld the territories vnto them that poſſeſſed them to bee holden in fee of the church, or didde geue authoritie to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3676:34"/>
others to ſubdue them, &amp; rule in their place.</p>
            <p>In this maner the moſt part of the citties of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magna,</hi> began to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by particular lordes, the moſt part of them, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of Vicars of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church. By this means <hi>Ferrara,</hi> giuen firſte in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment to <hi>Azzo</hi> of <hi>Eſté,</hi> was afterwards granted vnto him in title of a vicar ſhip, and in tract of time that familie was exalted to higher titles and digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie. Likewiſe <hi>Bologna</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied by <hi>Iohn Viſconte</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Millan,</hi> was afterwards giuen him as a vicarſhip, by the pope: &amp; for the ſame reaſons ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other territories in the <hi>Marque</hi> of <hi>Ancona,</hi> in the patrimony of ſaint <hi>Peter,</hi> and in <hi>Vmbria</hi> (which wee call now the dutchy of <hi>Spo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leto</hi>) many priuate Lords did riſe, being driuen ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, ſome againſt the wil of the pope, others by his conſent. The which alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations being likwiſe hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened in <hi>Lombardie,</hi> in the citties belonging to the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3676:35"/>
Empire, it chaunced ſome times, as the ſtate of mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters did change, that the Vicars of <hi>Romagna,</hi> and of other Eccleſiaſtical pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces did openly withdrawe themſelues from the nam of the church, and did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thoſe citties in fee of the Empire: as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, they which did oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie <hi>Millan, Mantua,</hi> and other imperiall poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in <hi>Lombardy,</hi> didde holde them in fee of the pope.</p>
            <p>In the meane while, al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit the citty of Rome did retaine the name and lord ſhip of the church, notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it was gouerned by their owne cittizens. And although at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning when the popes did returne from <hi>Auignon</hi> they were obeied as lords, notwithſtanding a lyttle while after, the <hi>Romaines</hi> hauing created a newe kind of magiſtrate which they called <hi>Banderez,</hi> they returned to their ancient ſtubborneſſe: whervppon the Popes hauing verye ſmal authoritie left them, they withdrew themſelus from Rome, vntill ſuche
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3676:36"/>
time that the <hi>Romaines</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing growne very poore, and great diſorders ſprunge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them thorow the ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence of the courte conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the yeare 1400. drew neer, in the which they hoped, that by the pope his reſidence there, there would be a great concourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from all partes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome by reaſonne of the <hi>Iubile,</hi> they humbly beſought the pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> that hee would vouchſafe to returne thither againe, offering im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vpon his comming to aboliſh their <hi>Banderez,</hi> &amp; to ſubmit themſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his obedience. Vnder which conditions the pope returning to Rome, whileſt the cittizens did altogither buſy themſelues, to the gain &amp; profite they receiued that yeare, he tooke the abſolute gouernement of the cittye vpon him, fortified the caſtle Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> and placed a guard of Soldiors therein: ſo that his ſucceſſors vntill the time of <hi>Eugenius,</hi> though with muche trouble often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, did notwithſtanding thorowly eſtabliſh their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and gouerned the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3676:37"/>
citty afterwardes without any contradiction.</p>
            <p>Theſe foundations being laid, and by theſe meanes, the popes being exalted to temporall authority, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by little and little the ſaluation of ſoules, and the commandementes of God, turning al their thoughtes to become great in this world, vſing ſpirituall iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and miniſter to attain to temporall gouernement, they began rather to ſeeme ſecular princes, then Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. They employed all their care, and buſied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not for the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of religion, not in zeal, and Charity towards their neighbors, but to raiſ arms and to make warre againſt Chriſtians, touching holye ſacrifices with their bloodie thoughts and handes: yea their whole ſtudy was to heape vp treaſure togither, to inuent new lawes, newe guiles, new ſleights to get mony on euery ſide, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard or reſpect to vſe ſpirituall weapons, to this end onely, &amp; to ſel with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out ſhame, both ſacred and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3676:38"/>
prophane things. Riches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpred ouer all their court, there followed pompe, riot, &amp; vnhoneſt cuſtoms, luſtes, and abhominable pleaſures: ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no care of their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſors, no thoght of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of the maieſty, belonging to ſo ſacred a function; but in ſteade therof ambitious &amp; peſtilent deſires to aduance themſelus their ſons, their nephewes &amp; kinſfolk, not onely to immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate welth and riches, but to kingdoms and principalities: making diſtribution of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and offices of profit, not to worthy and vertuous men, but commonlye either ſelling them to thoſe that wold giue moſt largly for them: or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtowing them vpon ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as either for their ambi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, couetouſnes, or other vil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lanous &amp; deteſtable pleſures, did iump and agree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. Thorowe which deedes of theirs, the reuerence which was wont to be born them, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing altogither fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> heart of men, neuertheleſſe their au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thority is ſtill vphelde, partly through the mighty name &amp; powreful maieſty of religion, being likewiſe greatly ayded thorow the means they haue to gratifie great princes, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3676:39"/>
thoſe which bear any authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty about them, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal liuings &amp; dignities. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon it commeth to paſſ, that they knowing right well, in what great regarde they are amongeſt men, and that they which take armes againſte them, are to expect the blot of reprochful infamie, and often times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hatred of other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which doe oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to thoſe enterpriſes, &amp; that whatſoeuer happeneth, ſmall aduauntage ariſeth to their enimies, that they being Conquerors, and getting the vpper hand, they vſe the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at their diſcretion, beeing ouercome they eſcape vppon ſuch conditions as they liſt: &amp; further ſtirred vp, and pricked forward, with a couetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to aduance their kindred, from priuate callinges, vnto princely eſtates, they haue a long while byn often the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of wars and newe fire in <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But returning to my princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal purpoſe, from the which the moſt iuſt grief of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publike loſſe &amp; ouerthrowe hath with more vehemency drawne me, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of a hiſtory dooth wel permit. I ſay that the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Romagna,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="fre" type="discourse">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3676:8"/>
            <head>Alius locus libro IIII. fol. 156. verſu. <hi>44.</hi> poſt Conceſsit.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>D cuius rei &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum aliarum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentibus tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ribus geſtarum clariorem notitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, res ipſa poſcit, vti quid iuris in Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>inia, quae nunc Romagna dicitur, oppidis aliiſque complu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ribus quae vel nunc poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, vel antea variis tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poribus poſſederunt, Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mani pontifices habeant, dicatur: quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pacto ab i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio rerum ſacraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtrationi duntaxat prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecti, ad regna &amp; imperia peruenerint: ad hoc vt id etiam tanquam his annex um &amp; coniunctum, quae ob has atque alias cauſas contentiones diuerſis te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus inter Pontifices at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Imperatores extite rint, commemoretur.</p>
            <p>Pontifices Romani, quo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3676:9"/>
ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> primus Petrus apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus fuit, accepta ab Ieſu Chriſto in rebus ſacris ac diuinis auctoritate, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, ſubmiſſione, patienti a, ſpiritu ſacro &amp; prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is magni, per illorum initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, non modò potentia ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uili &amp; mundana penitus nudati, uerumetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab illa uexati, diu obſcuri ac fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rè ignorati fuere: eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine nulla re magis quàm ſuppliciis &amp; cruciatibus perfere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis innoteſcente: quae unà cum iis qui eos ſe quebantur, ſuſtineba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> etſi cum propter infinitam multitudinem diuerſarum nationu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſectarum quae in vrbem Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confluxe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant, parum Chriſtianoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> progreſſus &amp; actiones ani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maduerterentur, eſſent<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ab quorunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ui &amp; vexationibus immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, niſi ſi qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do illoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bliciritus ſilentio praeteri
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3676:10"/>
riri non poſſent: nihilomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus tamen aliqui alii ſiue innata feritate, ſiue deoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſano quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re perculſi, eos tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uarum ſuperſtitionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores, &amp; ſuae religionis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſores, atrociter perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. Hoc in ſtatu tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taria paupertate, tum vitae reliquae ſanctimonia, tum ſuppliciorum acerbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus clariſsimi, ad Silue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtri po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tificatum perſtite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Cuius temporibus quum ad Chriſtiana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinus moribus ſanctiſsimis Chriſtianoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; prodigiis ac miraculis, quae frequentiſsima in iis qui Chriſti veſtigia ſeque<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bantur, elucebant, per mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus, animum appuliſſet, Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifices à periculis in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus annos circiter trecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos uerſati fuerant, tuti, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius cultum diuinum ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ercere, rituſque Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3676:11"/>
palam profiteri. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mobrem factum eſt, vt par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tim moru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vitae admirati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one, partim praeceptorum quae noſtra religione con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, ſanctitate, partim quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> facilitate quadam mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, qua plerun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vel ambitione, vel metu, prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipis ſui exemplum imita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur, nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficè omnib. in locis propa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gari, paupertas uerò illa ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerdotum beata, diminui coepere. Nam Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus templo in Laterano diuo Ioanni, in Vaticano Petro apoſt. item<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Paulo, aliis<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> diuerſis in locis aedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficatis, ea non modo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioſis uaſis ornamentiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ditauit, uerumetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt ſarta tecta tueri, ac renouare quae extructa era<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſe<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rebus ſacris opera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> darent, ſuſtentare poſſent, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> aliis vectigalibus donauit: alii praeterea mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti poſt ſecuti, rati benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3676:12"/>
huiuſmodi faciliorem aditum incoeleſte regnum ſibi patefieri, aut noua ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truebant fana, ea<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> donis cumulabant: autiam extru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctis ſuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> portio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> attribuebant, quinetiam ſiue lege qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam inueterata, ſiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine, ad legis Moſeae exemplum, quiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> de ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonorum fructib. deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partem locis religioſis pendebat: ad quod qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem efficiendum, magno cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ardore excitabantur: quod viderent ab initio ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerdotes, eo excepto, quod ad parciſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> victu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi reſeruabant, quicquid reliquum erat, partim in aedificia religioſa, eorum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſupellectilem, partim in egenos alioſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pios vſus impendere: cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nondum ſuperbia &amp; ambitio in eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pectorib. inſediſſet, ab vniuerſis qui vbique e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Chriſtianis omnium
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3676:13"/>
omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiarum ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cuſtos, &amp; tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri apoſt. ſucceſſor epiſc. Romanus agnoſcebatur: primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod ea ciuitas ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuam antiquam dignitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tanquam reliquaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caput &amp; princeps, Imperii no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men maieſtatem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> retine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat: de inde quod illinc in bona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Europae partem reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gio chriſtiana diffuſa erat: poſtremo qui a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantin. à Silueſtro ritu chriſtiano aquis initiatus, eiuſmodi auctoritatem in eo at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in eius ſucceſſorib. libenter agnouerat. Fama quoque eſt, Conſtantinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Orientis prouinciarum motib. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii ſedem Byza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, poſt de ſuo nomine Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nopolim appellata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre compulſum, pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci Romanae vrbis, aliarum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> &amp; vrbium &amp; regionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Italia, Imperium donaſſe. Quae fama qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis à ſequen tib. pontificib. dil igenter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3676:14"/>
fuerit enutrita &amp; ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta, eorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> auctoritate à multis credita, eſt nihilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus cùm ab ſcriptorib. grauiſſimis, tum vero reb. ipſis refutata. Illud autem certo conſtat, &amp; tunc &amp; longo poſt tempore, vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Italiam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nem tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperio Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obnoxiam, ab impera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torum miniſtris ac praefec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis fuiſſe gubernatam: nec deſunt qui, quicquid de Conſtantino &amp; Silueſtro dicitur (vſque adeo ſaepe profu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis in tenebris res ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuſtae demerſae latent) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darguant, oſtendant<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> eos longè diuerſis temporib. extitiſſe: nemo tamen ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, imperii Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polim tranſlatione ad po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificum potentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, viam eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe patefacta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex ea<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habuiſſe. Nam indies magis &amp; magis imperato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum auctoritate, tum ex il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum continua abſentia,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3676:15"/>
tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quòd grauiſſimis in Ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ente bellis diſtinerentur, in Italia debilitata, populus Romanus ab imperatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obedientia paulatim deſciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cens, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ob eam tem ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to magis po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifices praeſentes reſpiciens, eis coepit non obedientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidem, ſed vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luntariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quodda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um exhibere. Quanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne haec quidem niſi lentè ſeſe oſtenderunt, ob Gothoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Vandalorum aliarum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> barbararu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nationum in Ita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liam effuſiones: à quibus capta ſaepe ac direpta Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, &amp; pontificum nomen, quod ad ciuiles attinet res, in obſcuro penè co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacebat, &amp; imperatorum in Italia auctoritas euaneſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat: quandoquidem ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta cum ignominia praedae barbaris expoſitam deſere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bant. Aliarum nationu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus cum torrentis inſtar erupiſſet, Gothoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos ſeptuaginta potentia
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3676:16"/>
permanſit. Erant hi nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; profeſſione Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, genere à prima origine Scythae &amp; Dacae: quibus ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caeſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> armis Italia pul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis per Graecos iteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſt. tus coepit Italia gubernari: quorum qui caeteris impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabat, Graeca voce Hexar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus appellabatur, ſede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Rane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nae in vrbe veſtuſtiſsi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma, eiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> temporibus opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiſsima, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ob agribo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem frequentiſ. habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. Nam poſt magnum in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crementum ex Caeſaris Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſti at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum claſſe validiſs. ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum, quam in eius portu vr bi penè coniuncto, cuius nunc vix vllum extat veſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gium, continenter tenue runt, à multis belli ducib. deinde ab Theodorico Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rege, eiuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſucceſſo ribus fuerat habitata: qui quod imperatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſpecta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haberent, eam po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius quàm Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, regni ſui
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3676:17"/>
ſedem maris opportunita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Byzantio propioris duc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti delegerunt: quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tunitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hexarchi, &amp; ſi con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>traria ratione ſecuti, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ibi conſediſſent, Romanae vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, aliiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Italiae ciuitatibus proprios imponeba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectos, quos Duces appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labant. Hinc Rauennatis Hexarchatus nomen: quo nomine omnia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debantur, quae proprios Duces non habebant, ſed vni Hexarcho obtempera bant. Qua tempeſtate pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifices Romani ciuilis pote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtatis penitus expertes, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animis admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratione &amp; obſeruantia mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rib. ipſorum ab illa priſtina puritate iam fatiſcentibus, obſoleſcente, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratorib. ſubiecti, aetatem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebant: ſine quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quos Hexarchos dixi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus appellatos, auctorita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, quamuis ſacerdotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Romani ſuffragiis
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3676:18"/>
renunciati, ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſe propon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificib. gerere. ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum capere audeba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſcopi Conſtantino politanus &amp; Raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nas, quo nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religionis ſedes impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> armoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potentiam ſequi conſueuit, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no epiſcopo ſaepenumero de principatu diſputaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Caeterum haud multo poſt rerum mutatio conſecuta. Nam Longobardi, gens fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rociſsima, in Italiam ingreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſi, Galliam ciſalpinam oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuparunt: ab quorum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio, Longobardia eſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pellata. Adiecerunt etiam Rauennam cum Hexarcha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu vniuerſo: alias praeterea multas Italiae partes, armis Picenum vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> &amp; Spoletum &amp; Beneuentum prolatis: quibus in locis Duces à ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dictos imperare iuſſerunt, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> haec omnia dum impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratores partimignauia, par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tim Afiaticis bellis detenti
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3676:19"/>
rebus paru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proſpiciunt. Horum igitur auxiliis Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma deſtituta, cum nec iam Hexarchoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtratus eſſent in Italia, conſiliis at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> auctoritate pontificum gubernari coepit: qui cum aliquot annis pòſt vnà cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Romanis ab Longobard. opprimerentur, ad Pipini Francoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regis auxilia ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſe receperunt. Qui valido in Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exercitu, vbi Longobardi annos vl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra ducentos dominatum tenuerant, ducto, eos inde pepulit: partem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ipſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperii, quaſi belli iure parti, pontifici &amp; ecleſiae Romanae condonauit: in quibus non modo Vrbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Fanum Fortunae, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gubbium (Igninum olim) multa<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> alia Romae vicina oppida, verumetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rauen na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum Hexarchatu ſuo: quo contineri aiunt quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid à Placentiae &amp; Papiae finib. Ariminum vſque Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dum
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3676:20"/>
inter &amp; Appeninum, ſtagna ſiue paludes Vene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torum, &amp; Adriaticum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num clauditur: ad haec ip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſum Ariminum ad Togla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flumen, tunc Iſaurum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellatum. Pipino autem mortuo, cum denuò pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificibus Longobardi eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent infeſti, &amp; quae ipſis donata erant inuaderent, Carolus eius filius (qui poſt ob maximas victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Magni cognomentum merito eſt adeptus) eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperio funditus euerſo à patre eccleſiae Romanae donata comprobauit: &amp; nominatim Picenum &amp; Spoleti Ducatum, quo A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila oppidum, Brutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pars continetur, pontifici tum cùm Longo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bardis bellum gereret at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributa. Haec ſic habere certo affirmant, quib. pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificii quidam ſcriptores addunt, cundem Carolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3676:21"/>
eccleſiae donaſſe Liguria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad Varum amnem, Italiae terminum: Mantua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> item &amp; quicquid Longobardi in Foro Iulii, atque in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria poſſideba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> aliquis ſcribit de Corſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca inſula, toto<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> illo tractu qui Luna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter &amp; Parmam intereſt: ob quae beneficia regis Galliae celebrati, &amp; bonorib. à pontificib. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti, Chriſtianiſſimi appel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lationem ſunt conſecuti. Poſt etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anno Salutis oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingenteſimo, Leo po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifex vna cum populo Romano (veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pontifex, haud alia auctoritate, quam vt eius populi caput) eunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>met Carolum Romanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorum nominarunt, nomine quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ipſo hanc imperii partem ab impera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torib. Conſtantinopoli a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentibus ſeiungentes, tan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quam Roma prouinciae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Occidentis ab illis deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3676:22"/>
in periculis: proprioru principum tutela opus ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berent. Hac imperii di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractione, tranſmarini im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peratores, nec Siciliae inſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la, nec ea Italiae parte, quae ab vrbe ipſa Neapoli, Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fredoniam vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pertingens mari terminatur (quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſemper illorum imperium agnouerant) excluſi fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: nec ob id de conſuetu dine qua pontifices impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratorum, quorum nomine Roma gubernabatur, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritate confirmarentur, derogatum eſt: quinetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuis diplomatib. ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rae tempus his verbis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignabant: IMPERAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TE CAROLO DOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NO NOSTRO. In qua minime graui vel ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one, vel obſeruantia per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitere, du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rerum euentus animos addidere, vt ſuo ſe nutu regerunt: quippe cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperatorum potentia de
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3676:23"/>
bilitari coepiſſet, primum diſſidiis inter Caroli mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni poſteros, du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penes eos imperii ad principes Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manos tranſlatione, pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Caroli magni ſucceſſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ribus minime pares, ponti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fices populuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Ramanus, cuius magiſtratib. Roma coepit, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis perturbate &amp; confuſe gubernari: Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorum auctoritati qui buſcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> modis derogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, lege ſanxerunt, ne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inceps pontificum lectio, imperatorum auctoritate niteretur: quod quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per annos plures variè ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, prout rerum viciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitudine imperatorum po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentia aut ſurgebat, aut in clinabat. Quae poſteaqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad Othones Saxonas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium peruenit, aucta: Gregorius Quintus Otho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis tertii ſauore, qui tum Romae erat, ad ponrifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aſſumptus, hinc ſuae
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3676:24"/>
gentis amore, illinc Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quibuſda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iniuriis, impulſus, ſuo decreto le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendi imperatoris ius &amp; auctoritatem, ea forma quae ad haec vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tempora perducta ſeruatur, in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manorum nationem tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tulit: at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vt pontificib. in imperatores, auctorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> retineret, eiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vicem redderet, inter dixit ne quis imperatoris Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiúe appellatione, alióue nomine qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regis Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum &amp; Caeſaris vtere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ni prius imperii coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à pontifice (vnde mos inoleuit, vt ad capiendam coronam Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vaniant) accipiant. Caeterùm Otho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nib. extinctis, &amp; potentia imperatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quòd ad mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nos reges haereditario iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Imperium non veniret, Roma palàm ab illorum obedientia defecit: multae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vrbes Conrado Sueuo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3676:25"/>
imperante, rebellarunt: &amp; pontifices ſuae amplifican<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dae auctoritati intenti, Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ciuitatis dominatu prope modum obtineba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: ſaepe tamen propter populi in ſolentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; diſcordias, mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis difficultatib. laboraba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quem vt in officio contine<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent, Henrici ſecundi fauo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, qui tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Romae erat, pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificis creandi ius in cardi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nales ſolos tranſtulerant. Pontificu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magnitudini no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua acceſſio facta eſt. Nam cum Normanni, quorum primus Gulielmus Fera brachius eſt appellatus, ab imperio Conſtantino politano Apulia &amp; Cala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bria ſubtracta, Robertus Guicciardus ex illa gente vnus, ſiue vt colore iuris aliquo ſeſe muniret: ſiue quo aduerſus eos impera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tores potentia ſe armaret ſiue alia de cauſſa, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uento pontifici, quaſi pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificii
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3676:26"/>
iuris eſſet, reſtituto, Apuliae Calabriae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>patu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quaſi eccleſiae Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nae fundum recognouit: cuius exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plum Rogerius eius ſucceſſorum vnus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutus, inde pulſo, Guilel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo eade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> familia orto, poſt etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sicilia occupata, ferè anno Salutis M.C.XXX. haru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prouinciarum ius à pontifice accepit: eſt<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> rex vtriuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Siciliae, quaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vna vltra, altera cis fretum ſita eſt, appellatus. Ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> enim pontifices ambitione &amp; propria vtilitate adducti, aliena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cupiditatem &amp; vim fouere recuſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Hac iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſpecie freti, vlterius po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifices progreſsi (vt cupi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do humana gradu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiſtere nequit) quoſdam reges il<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis regnis quaſi contuma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces priuare coeperunt in alioſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> transferre: quo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ad Henricum Federici Barbaruſſae filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ab hoc ad
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3676:27"/>
Federicu ſecund. eius fili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um, quitres ordine Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni imperatores fuerunt, ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>regna peruenere. Verum cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Federicus pontificem bello perſequeretur, eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> illo tempore Guelforu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Gibellinoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> factiones excitatae, quarum alterius caput erat pontifex, alteri us imperator: pontifex, mortuo Federico, Carolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Andiouinorum &amp; Prouin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciae comitem (cuius antea facta mentio eſt) vtriuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Siciliae regem appellauit: hac lege vt quota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis, auri vnciarum ſena milia tribu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti nomine penderet: ac ne quis corum regum in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterum imperatoris Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani appellationem poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet admittere: quae excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ſemper ab eo tempore in regni Neapolitani di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plomate expreſſa fuit. na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Siciliae regnum pòſt à Tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raconenſib regib. occupa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3676:28"/>
à pontificum obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia ſeſe ſubduxit, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> à tributo pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Ad hoc obtinuit fama (etſi haud ita certa, quàm ea quae hactenusdicta ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) Mathildam principem in Italia praepotentem, eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiae eam partem Etruriae donaſſe, quae Peſcia torre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te &amp; Quirici caſtello in Senenſium finibus ab vna parte, ab altera mari in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro &amp; Tyberi amne, quae hodie Patrimonium Petri vulgo nominatur: &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alii, ab eadem Ferrari am eccleſiae donata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Haec poſtrema dubia fide retu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limus, caeterùm multo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis dubia quae ab aliquo ſcripta ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, videlicet, Auth pertum Longobardorum regem, flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ipſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, eidem eccleſiae alpes Coccias, in quib. Genua, &amp; quicquid ab ea in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:3676:29"/>
vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Romanorum patet: &amp; Luithprandum eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gentis regem, Sabi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nam Romae propinquam regionem, Narnia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conem, cum aliis quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam oppidis attribuiſſe. In hunc igitur modu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtatu variante, variae pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pontificum at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorum res fuere. Nam à primis imperatoribus per multa annorum curricula vexati, poſt Conſtantini ad Chriſtum conuerſione ab eo terrore liberati, reb. ſacris ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum operam dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, in reliquis imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum auctoritati ferè ſubie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cti, ſub eorum vmbra quie uerunt. In hoc humili ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu diutiſſime poſt vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>runt, ab imperatorum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercio, propter magnam in Italia Longobardorum potentiam ſeiuncti. Poſt autem Galliae regum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficio opib. &amp; potentia
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3676:30"/>
aucti, cum imperatoribus coniunctiſ. ſtetere, ab illo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auctoritate, dum impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratoria maieſtas in Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li magni poſteris ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacri animo pendentes, quod quidem fiebat, tum propter beneficia, viciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſim data, &amp; accepta, tum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ob imperatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiam: quae vbi pòſt coepit inclinare, &amp; quaſi flacceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſere, illorum amicitia pror ſus reiecta, ita ſe gerere coeperunt, quaſi pontifici ae dignitatis eſſet leges po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius imperatorib. dare'<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> accipere. Cum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> à veteri illo quo ſubiecti impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torib. ſtatu penitus abhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rerent, veriti<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ne illi Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> alibi antiqua im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii iura recuperare, vt quida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illorum aut poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia maiore, aut animo ere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctiore efficere conaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, tentarent, armata vi ſeſe imperatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potentiae, ab illis tyrannis qui ſe princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3676:31"/>
appellabant, &amp; ab illis vrbib. quae ſeſe in liberta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem vindicauerant, nec ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imperii auctoritatem ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcebant, adiuti, oppone<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bant. Hinc factum eſt, vt pontifices ſibi indies plu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra maiora<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> arrogantes, terrorem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> armoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtium in res terrenas cadu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cas vertentes, ius ſibi at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> auctoritatem in imperato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, quaſi Chriſti in terris vices gerentes, aſſumpſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>runt: affirma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ad ſe mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis in reb. regnorum atque imperiorum procuratio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nem pertinere. Qua per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuaſione freti, imperato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rib. interdum imperii dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitatem abrogabant, Sep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temuiros Auguſtales, vt alios in eorum locum ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogarent, incitaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Viciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſim quoque imperatores, aut ipſi creabant nouos pontifices, aut vt crearen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur procurabant. Ex his controuerſiis, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> etiam
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3676:32"/>
quod pontifices per a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nos ſeptuaginta Auenione ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dem habuiſſent, nec non ex illo eccleſiae diſſidio, quod in Italia pontifice Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuertente, eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortum, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiae ſtatus admodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concuſſus ac de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitatùs eſſet, factum eſt, vt in oppidis eccleſiae ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectis, praecipuè vero in ea Italiae parte, quae olim Gallia togata dicta eſt, complures in eis ciues po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentia caeteris ſuperiores, in ſua, quiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> patria tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occupare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: quos pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifices aut perſequeba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, aut, ſi ad eos opprime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dos impares eſſent, quaſi eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiae beneficio regnare iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebant, aut aliis in eos excitatis, regna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ius attri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buebant. In hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o igitur mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dum Galliae togatae oppi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da, proprios dominos ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleroſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quaſi eccleſiae vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carios habere coeperunt. Eodem modo Ferraria
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3676:33"/>
Actio Ateſtino à pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce gubernanda tradita, ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dem eſt poſt beneficii no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine attributa: ex quo de inde ea familia illuſrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib. honoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> titulis eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornata. Sic Bononia ab Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anne Vicecomite Medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanenſium archiepiſcopo occupata, eidem pari iure conceſſa fuit. Iiſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> de cauſis in multis Piceni oppidis, diui Petri Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio, &amp; Vmbria, quae nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c Ducatus appellatur, plures reguli, pars inuito, pars ad conſentiendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acto po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifice, ſunt exorti: nec Longobardia, in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii praeſertim oppidis, ab huiuſmodi mutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nib. immunis fuit: ſicut qui in Flaminia at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> aliis pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificiis locis dominaban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur à pontificum obedien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia deficientes, ad impera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auctoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confuge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rent: &amp; viciſſim qui Medi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>olanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Mantua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; alia im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3676:34"/>
oppida tenebant, à pontificibus regnandi ius obtinerent. Roma verò quanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiae temporib. illis prae ſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, magiſtratib. tamen re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gebatur propriis &amp; ſuis: &amp; qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis initio cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Auenione in Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſt liminio re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſſ. tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini ag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſcerentur, paulo tamen poſt Romani creato ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratu, quod Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derenſiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appellabant, in veterem contumacia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recidere: vn de cum pontificu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auctori tas apud eos eſſet perexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua, &amp; ipſi alio tranſlata ſede, Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reliquere, do nec Romani ad pauperta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem redacti, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propter eius abſentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confuſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delapſi, cum annus milleſimus quadrin genteſimus appropinqua ret: in quo anno ſi ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex in Vrbe eſſet, ſperaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ingente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fore propter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecularem, quem Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leum
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3676:35"/>
voca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>curſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, precib. qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> demiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſimis Bonifacium pontifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cem orarunt, Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret: id ſi faceret, Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derenſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>um magiſtratu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abrogatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, ſe<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ei obſequentis in omnib. futuros. His condi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tionib. in Vrbem reuerſus dum Romani illius anni quaeſtum vnum attendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, pontifex occupato omni Vrbis imperio, Angelica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> arcem communiuit, ei<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> praeſidium impoſuit: cuius ſucceſſores ad Eugenium vſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> etſi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paucis difficul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatib. conflictati, nihil omi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus dominatu poſt plenè ſtabilito, inſecuti pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces citra vllam controuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiam, Romae ſunt pro ſua libidine dominati. His igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fundamentis &amp; modis ad terrenam potentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ela<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti, ac ſenſim animarum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis, diuinorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> praecep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torum obliti, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ad mun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dana imperia omni cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3676:36"/>
conuerſi, nec diui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na auctoritate alio, quàm quaſi, telo &amp; inſtrumento reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fragilium abutentes, principes potius gentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quàm rerum ſacraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices videri coeperu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum curae &amp; negocia, non ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitae ſanctimonia, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis incrementa, non erga Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; homines cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritas, ſed exercitus, ſed bel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la in Chriſtianos, cogitati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>one &amp; manib. ſanguine re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſperſis ſacra tracta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: ſed pecuniae imme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa cupido, nouae leges, nouae artes, uouae inſidiae ad pecunia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vndi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> cogenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in hunc fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audaſiſſimè arma coele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtia vibrare, profanaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crarum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> rerum nundina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impudentiſ. exerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: hinc opes in immenſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adauctae, &amp; in totam ipſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum aulam effuſae: ex qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus faſtus, luxus, mores turpis. libidines, volupta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nefandae: nulla ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoribus,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3676:37"/>
nulla maieſtatis perpetuae pontificatus ſolli citudo: ſed horum loco cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pido anxia &amp; peſtifera, fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, nepotes, item alios ſibi coniunctos &amp; neceſſarios non modò ad opes immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratas, verumetiam ad reg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na &amp; imperia euehendi: no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iam honores &amp; emolumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta in merentes &amp; bonos conferendo, ſed plerunque auctionando, aut in homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ambitione, auaritia, &amp; pudendis voluptatibus per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditos effu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dendo. His mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus effectum eſt, vt excuſſa penitus ex animis hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> illa vetere erga pontifices reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia: tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex parte, eo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auctoritas religionis, qua nihil in terris ad homines vel impelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dos, vel retinen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dos, pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius inuenitur, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine &amp; maieſtate, faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te qua pollent, principibus at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> iis qui apud illos maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè poſſunt, ſacris beneficiis &amp; honoribus conferendis,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3676:38"/>
gratificandi adiuta ſuſtente tur. Qui cum ſciant magna ſe in admiratione mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe: &amp; qui aduerſus eos ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſumunt, eos grauis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famiae notam, &amp; ſaepenume<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro aliorum principu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> odia ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bire: ac quomodocun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> res cadat, perexiguum emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ad eos à quib. op pugnantur, redundare: &amp; victores ex ſuo arbitrio vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoria vſuros: victos, quib. velint conditionib. pacem habituros: ad haec ſuos pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinquos ex priuata co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ad principatus attollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di cupidine inflammati, iam per multos annos bellorum auctores, nouoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diorum faces in Italia extite runt. Sed vt ad id à quo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſſimus publici damni do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lor me longius acriuſque quàm leges hiſtoriae forſita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> permittant, abduxit, reuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tamur. Aomili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Flamin. &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="ita" type="discourse">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3676:8"/>
            <head>Diſcorſo leuato del tutto via dell'hiſtoria nel quarto libro a carte <hi>119.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Er la dichiaratione della qual coſa, et di molt' altre ſuccedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ne tempi ſeguenti, ricerca la materia che ſi faccia men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione, che ragioni habhia la Chieſa ſopra le terre di Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>magna &amp; ſopra molte altre, le quali, o ha in varij tempi poſſedute, o hora poſſiede: e in che modo iuſtituita da prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipio meramente per l'ammi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtratione ſpirituale, ſia peruenuta alli ſtati, &amp; alli imperij mondani: &amp; ſimil mente, che ſi narri come coſa connexa, quali contentioni ſianno ſtate per queſte &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre cagioni in diuerſi tempi, tra e pontifici et gl'Impera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dori.</p>
            <p>E pontefici Romani de quali il primo fu l'Apoſtolo Piero,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3676:9"/>
fondata da Gieſu Chriſto l'autorità loro nelle coſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituali, grandi dî charita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, d humiltà, di patientia, di ſpirito &amp; di miracoli, furo no ne loro principii non ſolo al tutto ſpogliati di potenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a temporale ma perſeguitati da quella ſtettono per molti anni oſcuri &amp; quaſi incogni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti, non ſi manifeſtando il no me loro per alcuna coſa piu che ne ſuplicij, e quali inſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me con quelli che gli ſeguita uono quaſi ſoſteneuano: per che ſe bene per la moltitudi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne innumerabile, &amp; per le di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe nationi, &amp; proſeſſioni che erano in Roma, fuſſino qualche volta poco atteſie progreſſi loro, &amp; alcuni delli Imperadori non gli perſegui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taſſino ſe no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quanto pareua che le attioni loro publiche non poteſſino eſſere con ſilen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio trapaſſata, non dimeno alcuni altri, o per crudeltà, o
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3676:10"/>
per l amore alli dij proprij, gli perſeguitarono atroceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te come induttori di nuoue ſuperſtitioni, &amp; deſtruttori della vera religione.</p>
            <p>Nel qual ſtato chiariſſimi per la voluntaria pouertà, per la ſantità della vita, e per e martyrij, continuarono inſino à Silueſtro pontifice: a tempo del quale eſſendo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuto alla fede Chriſtiana Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantino Jmperadore, moſſa da coſtumi ſantisſimi, &amp; da miracoli che in quelli che il nome di Chriſto ſeguitaua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no continuamente ſi vedeua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no, rimaſono e pontifici ſicu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri da pericoli, ne quali erano ſtati circa a trecento anni, &amp; liberi d'eſſercitare publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camente il culto diuino &amp; ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti Chriſtiani.</p>
            <p>Onde per la riuerenza de
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3676:11"/>
costumi loro, per e precetti ſanti, che contìene in ſe la noſtra religione, &amp; per la prontezza che è negl'huom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi à ſeguitare, o per ambiti one il piu delie volte, o per ti more, l'eſempio del ſuo pren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipe, cominciò a ampliarſi per tutto marauiglioſamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te el nome Christiano, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieme a diminuire la pouertà de cherici. per che Conſtanti no hauendo edificata a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma la chieſa di ſan Gioua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni in Laterano, la chieſa di ſan Pietro in Vaticano, quella di ſan Paulo, &amp; molte altre in diuerſi luoghi, le dotò non ſolo di ricchi vaſi &amp; orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti, ma anchora, perche ſi poteſſino conſeruare &amp; rino<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uare, &amp; per le fabriche, &amp; ſo ſtentatione di quelli che vi eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſercitauano il culto diuino, di poſſeſſioni &amp; d'altre en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate: &amp; ſucceſſiuamente molti ne tempi che ſeguitaro no, perſuadendoſi con l'elemo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3676:12"/>
ſine e con legati alle chieſe, farſi facile l'acquiſto del reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no celeſte, o fabricauano, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauano altre chieſe, o alle gia edificate diſpenſauano parte delle ricchezze loro: anzi o per legge, o per inuetterata conſuetudine ſeguitando l'eſ ſempio del teſtamento vecchi o, ciaſcuno, de frutti de beni proprij pagaua alle chieſe la decima parte, excitandoſi a queſte coſe gl'huomini con grande ardore, per che da principio e cherici, da quello infuora che era neceſſario per il moderatiſſimo vitto loro, tutto il rimamente par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te nelle fabriche &amp; paramen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti delle chieſe, parte in opere piatoſe &amp; charitatiue diſtri buiuano:</p>
            <p>Ne eſſendo anchora entrata ne petti loro la ſuperbia &amp; l'ambitione, era ricodoſciu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to viuerſalmente da Chriſti ani per ſuperiore di tutte le
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3676:13"/>
chieſe, &amp; di tutta l'amini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratione ſpirituale el veſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo di Roma come ſucceſſore dell'apoſtolo Piero: &amp; per che quella citta per la ſua an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticha degnita &amp; grandezza riteneua come capo delle al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre el nome &amp; la maieſtà del imperio, &amp; perche da quella ſiera diffuſa la fede Chriſtia na nella maggior parte dell'Europa, &amp; perche Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no battezzato da Silueſtro, tale autorità volentieri in lui &amp; ne ſuoi ſucceſſori ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uea riconoſciuta.</p>
            <p>E fama oltre a queſte co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, che Coſtantino coſtretto dalli accidenti delle prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie Orientali a transferire la ſedia dell'imperio nella città di Bizantio chiamata del ſuo nome Conſtantinopo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li, donò a pontefici el domino di Roma, &amp; di molt' altre città &amp; regioni d'Italia: la qual fama, benche diligente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente nutricata da pontefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3676:14"/>
che ſuccederono, &amp; per l'au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torità loro creduta da molti, e dagl'autori piu probabili riprouata, &amp; molto piu dal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le coſe ſteſſe: per che è mani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſtiſſimo, che all hora &amp; longo tempo di poi, fu ammi niſtrata Roma &amp; tutta l'Ita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia ſuddita all imperio, da e magiſtrati deputati dag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im peradore. Ne manca chi re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>darguiſca (ſi profunda è ſpeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo nelle coſe tanto antiche loſcurita) tutto quello che ſi dice di Coſtantino &amp; di Sil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſtro, affermando eſſi eſſere ſtati in diuerſi tempi: maniu no nega che la traſlatione della ſed ia dell imperio a Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantinopoli, fu la prima ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gine della potentia de ponte fici, indebolendo in progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo di tempo l'autorita de gl'Jmperadori in Jtalia per la continua abſentia loro, &amp; per le difficulta che hebbono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nell Oriente, el populo Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano diſcoſtandoſi da gli
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3676:15"/>
Jmperadori, &amp; però tanta piu deferendo a pontefici, co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minciò a preſtar loro non ſub iettione, ma ſpontaneamen te vn certo obſequio.</p>
            <p>Benche qucſte coſe non ſi demonſtrorono ſe non lentà<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente per le inundationi de Gothi, de Vandali, &amp; d'altre barbare nationi che ſopra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennono in Jtalia: dalle qua li preſa &amp; ſaccheggiata piu volte Roma, era quanto alle coſe temporali obſcuro &amp; ab ietto el nome de pontefici, &amp; piccoliſſima in Italia l'auto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rità de gl'Imperadori, poi che con tanta ignominia la laſciauano in preda de bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari.</p>
            <p>Trale quali nationi, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do ſtato l'impeto delle altre quaſi come vn torrente, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuò per ſettanta anni la potentia de Gothe, gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te di nome &amp; di profeſſione Chriſtiana, &amp; vſcita dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la prima origine ſua
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3676:16"/>
delle parti di Dacia &amp; di Tartaria: la quale eſſendo finalme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ſtata cacciata d'I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia dalle arme dell'Jmpera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dori, cominciò di nuoua Jta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia a gouernarſi per magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrati Greci, de quali, quello cheera ſuperiore a tutti, det to con Greco vocabulo Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archo, riſedeua a Rauenna città antichiſſima, &amp; all'ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra molto ricca &amp; molto fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente per la fertilità del pae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, &amp; perche dopo l'augmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to grande che hebbe per l'ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mata potente tenuta conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuamente da Ceſare Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto &amp; da altri Imperadori nel porto quaſi congiuntoli &amp; che hora non appariſce, eraſtata habitata da molti capitani, &amp; poi per longo te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>po da Theodorica Re de Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thi et da e ſuoi ſucceſſori: quali hauendo a ſuſpetto la potentia de gl Imp. haueua no eletta quella piu toſto che Roma, per ſedia del regno
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3676:17"/>
loro, per l'oportunità del ſuo mare piu propinquo a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopoli, la quale oportu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nita, benche per contraria ragione, ſeguitando li Exar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chi, fermati quiui, deputaua no al gouerno di Roma &amp; dell'altre città d'Italia Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrati particolari, ſotto ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolo di Duchi. Da queſto hebbe origine el nome del Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arcato di Rauenna: ſotto el qual nome, ſi comprendeua tutto quollo che non hauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Duchi particolari, vbidi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua immediatamente all'Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co.</p>
            <p>Nel qual tempo e pontefi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ci Romani, priuati in tutto di potentia temporale, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lentata per la diſſimulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne de coſtumi loro, gia comin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciati a tranſcorrere, la reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rentia ſpirituale, ſtauano quaſi come ſubiecti all Jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradori, ſenza la conferma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione de quali, o de loro Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archi, benche eletti dal clero
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3676:18"/>
&amp; populo Romano, non ardi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uano di exercitare, o di ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cettare el ponteficato: anzi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gli epiſcopi Coſtantinopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tano &amp; Rauennate (per che communemente la ſedia del la religione ſeguita la poten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia dell Imperio &amp; dell ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me) diſputauano ſpeſſo del la ſuperiorità con l'Epiſcopo Romana. Ma ſi mutò non molto poi lo ſtato delle coſe: perche e Longobardi, gente ferociſſima, entrati in Italia occuparono la Gallia Ciſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pina, la quale dall imperio loro preſe il nome di Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardia, Rauenna con tutto l'Exarcato, &amp; molte altre parti d'Jtalia: &amp; ſi diſteſe ſeno l'arme loro inſino nella Marca Anconitana, &amp; a Spuleto, &amp; a Beneuento: ne quali due luoghi creorono Duchi particolari, non pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uedendo a queſte coſe parte per la iguauia loro, parte per le difficulta che haueuano in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3676:19"/>
Aſiagli Jmperadori: da gl'a iuti de quali Roma abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata, ne eſſendo piu il magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrato delli Exarchi in Jta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, cominciò a regnerſi eo, conſigli &amp; con l'autorità de pontifici: e quali, dopo molto tempo eſſendo inſieme co' Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mani oppreſſati da Longo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bardi, ricorſeno finalmente alli aiuti di Pipeno re di Francia: el qual paſſato con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potente eſſercito in Italia, hauendoui e Longobardi do minato gia piu di duce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni, cacciatigli d'vna parte del loro imperio, donò (come diuentate ſue per ragione di guerra) al pontifice &amp; alla chieſa Romana non ſolo Vr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bino, Fano, Agobbo &amp; molte terre vicine a Roma, ma eti amdio Rauenna col ſuo Ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ercato, ſotto el quale dicono includeruiſi tutto quello che ſi contiene da confini di Pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenza contigui al territorio di Pauia in fino a Arimini,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3676:20"/>
tra el fiume del Po, el monte Apenino, gli ſtagni o vero pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ludo de venetiani, &amp; el ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Adriatico: &amp; di piu Ari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mini infino al fiume della To<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glia, detto all hora Iſauro.</p>
            <p>Ma dopo la morte di Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pino, moleſtando di nuouo; Longobardi e pontefici, et quello che era ſtato donato lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro, Carlo ſuo figliuolo (quan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do che poi per le vittorie gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſſime che hebbe, fu merita mente cognominato Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no) diſtrutto del tutto l'impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rio loro, confermò la donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one fatta alla chieſa Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na dal padre, &amp; approuò l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerſi, mentre che guerriggia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua co' Longobardi, date al Pontifice la Marca d'An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cona &amp; el Ducato di Spole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, el quale comprendeua la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>città dell'Aquila, &amp; vna parte dell'Abruzzi. Affer manſi queſte coſe per certe, alle quali aggiung ono alcuni ſcrittori Eceleſiaſtici, Carlo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3676:21"/>
hauer donato alla Chieſa la Liguria infino al fiume del Varo vltimo confine d'Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, Mantoua &amp; tutto quel lo che e Longobardi poſſede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uano nel Friuoli &amp; in Hiſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>a: &amp; el medeſimo ſcriue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuno altro de l'Iſola di Corſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ca, &amp; di tutto el territorio che ſi contiene tra la città di Luni &amp; di Parma. Per e qua li meriti e re di Francia ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrati &amp; exaltati da ponti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fici, conſeguirono el titolo di Re Chriſtianiſſimi: &amp; di poi l'anno ottocenteſimo della noſtra ſalute, Leone pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce inſieme col populo Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, non con altra autorita, che del pontef. come capo di quel popolo, eleſſeno el mede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſimo Carlo per Imperadore Romano, ſepar ando etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dio nel nome queſta parte dell im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perio da gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Jmperadori che habitauano a Coſtantinopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li: come ſe Roma e le prouin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie Occidentali non difeſe da pro
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3676:22"/>
loro, haueſſino biſogno d'eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſere difeſa da proprio prenci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe. Per la quale diuiſione, non furono priuati gl Jmpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radori Coſtantinopolitani, ne dell'Iſola di Sicilia, ne di quella parte d Italia, la qua le diſcorrendo da Napoli a Manfredonia è terminata dal mare, perche erano ſtate continuamente ſotto quell'Jmperadori. Ne ſi derogò per queſte coſe alla conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dine, che la elettione de pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teficifuſſi confirmata da gl'Imperadori Romani, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me de quali ſi gouernana la città di Roma: anzi e ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici nelle bolle, ne priuilegij &amp; nelle conceſſioni loro, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primeuano con queſte parole formali el tempo della ſcrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, Jmperante il tale im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradore ſignore noſtro.</p>
            <p>Nella quale non graue o ſoggezzione, o dependenza continuorono in fino a tanto che e ſucceſſi delle coſe no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> det
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3676:23"/>
tono loro animo a reggerſi per ſe ſteſſi. Maeſſendo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minciata a indebolire la po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentia de gl'Imperadori, pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma per le diſcordie nate tra e deſcendenti mediſimi di Carlo Magno, mentre che in loro riſedeua la degnità Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periale, &amp; di eſſere ſtata tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſportatane prencipi The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſchi non potenti come era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ſtati per la grandezza del regno di Francia e ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſori di Carlo, e pontefici &amp; el popolo Romano, da magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrati del quale cominciò Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma, benche tumultuoſamen te, a gouernirſi, derogando in tutte le coſe quanto pote<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ua no alla iuriſdittione dell'Jmperadori ſtatuirono per legge, che non piu la elezzio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne de pontifici haueſſe a eſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re confermata da loro: il che ſi oſſeruo diuerſamente ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do che per la variatione del le coſe ſurgeua o declinaua piu la potentia Jmperiale.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3676:24"/>
La quale eſſendo accreſciuta poi che l'Imperio perue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gli Otthoni di Saxonia, Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gorio quinto di natione The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſco, eletto pontifice per fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uore d'Otthone Terzo che e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra preſente, moſso dell amore della propria natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, &amp; ſdeg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nato per le perſecutioni ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceuute da Romani, tranferi per ſuo decreto nella natione Germanica la facultà di e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leggere glimperadori Roma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni, in quella forma, che infino all et à noſtra ſi oſſerua, vie ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do agli eletti (per riſerua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re a pontefici qualche premi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nentia) di non vſare eltito lo d'imperadori, o di Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti, ſe prima no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riceueuano la corono dell'imperio (donde è introdotto il venire à Roma a incoronarſi) &amp; di no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſar prima altro titolo che di Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de Romani &amp; di Caeſare. Mamancati poi gli Otthoni &amp; diminuita la potentia de gli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Jmperadori, perche l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perio no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuaua herédi
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3676:25"/>
tario in Re gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di, Roma a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te ſi ſutraſſe dalla obedienza loro: &amp; molte cit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tà, qna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do imperaua Curado Sueuo ſi rebellorono: &amp; e po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tefici atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ad ampliare la propria autorità, domina uano quaſi Roma, benche ſpeſſo per la inſolentia &amp; per le diſcordie del popolo vi ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſſino molte difficulta: el quale per reprimere, haueua no gia per fauore di Henrico ſecondo Jmperadore che era a Romo, trasferita per legge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Cardinali ſoli l'autorità di creare el pontefice. Alla grandezza de quali ſuccedet te nuouo augmento, perche haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do e Normanni, de qua li il primo fu Gulielmo cog nominuto Ferrabraccio, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpata all'imperio Coſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nopolitano la Puglia &amp; la Calabria, Roberto Guicciar do vno di eſſi o per fortificar ſi con queſto colore di ragio ne, o per eſſer piu potente a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3676:26"/>
difenderſi co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tro a quegli Jm<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peradori, o, per altra cagio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e reſtituito Beneue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to come di ragione eccleſiaſtica, riconob be el Ducato di Puglia di Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>labria in feudo dalla Chieſa Romana, il cui eſſempio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do Ruggieri vno de ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oi ſucceſſori, &amp; haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſcac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciato del ducato di puglia, &amp; di Calauria Guiglielmo del la medeſima famiglia, &amp; oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupata poi la Sicilia, riconob be circa l'anno mille ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta queſte prouincie in feudo dalla Chieſa ſotto titolo di Re di ambidue le Sicilie, l'u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na di la, baltra di qua dal Faro, non recuſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do e pontefi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ci di ſome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tare per l'ambitio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; vtilità propria, l'altrui vſurpatione &amp; violentia: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le quali ragioni pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre piu oltre, come no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mai ſi ferma la cupidita humana cominciorono e po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifici a pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uare di quelli regni alcuno de Re contumaci à loro co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>damenti,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3676:27"/>
&amp; a concedergli ad altri, nel qualmodo perue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neno in He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rico figliuolo di Federigo Barbaroſſa, &amp; da Henrico in Fede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſuo figliuolo tut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatre ſucceſſiuame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radori Romani Maeſse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do Federigo diue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tato acerrimo perſecutore della Chieſa, &amp; ſuſcitate a tempi ſuoi le fat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioni Guelfa &amp; Ghibellina, dell'vna delle qualiera capo el pontefici, dell'altra lo Jm<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peradore, morto Federigo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cedette la inueſtitura di que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti regni a Carlo conte d'An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gio &amp; di Prouenza, del quale di ſopra eſtata fatta mentio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cenſo di vncie ſemilia d'oro per ciaſcuno anno, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conditione, che alcuno per l'auenire di quelli Reno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſse accettare lo imperio Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mano: la quale conditione è ſtata poi ſempre ſpecificata nelle inueſtiture del regno di Napoli: per che el regno dell'Iſoſola di Sicilia occupato
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3676:28"/>
dae Re d'Aragonia, ſi ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò dopo pochi anni nel cenſo &amp; nelle recognitioni del feis do dalla vbidienza della chie ſa. Ha anco ottenuto la fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, benche no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tanto certa qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to ſono le coſe precede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti che molto prima la Conteſſa Mathelda prencipeſſa in Ita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia molto potente, donò alla Chieſa quella parte della Toſcana, la quale termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta dal torrente di Peſcia, &amp; dal caſtello di ſan Quirico nel contado di Siena da vna parte, &amp; dall'altra dal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re di ſotto, &amp; dal fiume del Teuere, hoggi detta il Patri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monio di ſan Piero: Et ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giungono altri che dalla me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſima Conteſſa fu donata alla Chiſa la città di Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. Non ſono certe queſte vl time coſe: ma è anchora piu dubbio quello che è ſtato ſcritto da qualcuno, che Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thperto Re de Longobardi, ſiorendo el regno loro, gli do
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3676:29"/>
nòl Alpe Coccie, nelle quali dicono includerſi Genoua, &amp; tutto quello che ſi contiene da Genoua infino a confini della Prouenza: &amp; che Lui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thprando Re della medeſima natione gli donò la Sabina, paeſe propinquo a Roma, Narni &amp; Ancona, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certe altre terre. Coſi variando lo ſtato delle coſe, furono ſimil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente varie le coſe de Ponte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fici con gl'imperadori. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che eſſendo ſtati perſeguita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti per molte età ne principij da gl'imperadori, &amp; di poi liberati per la couuerſione di Coſtantino da queſto terrore ſi ripoſorono: ma attende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ſolamente alle coſe ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li &amp; poco meno che interame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſudditi, per molti anni ſot to l'ombra loro, viſſono di poi lunghiſſimo tempo in baſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo ſtato, et ſeparati totalmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te dal commertio loro per la grandezza de Longobardi in Jtalia: ma poi peruenuti
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3676:30"/>
per beneficio de Re di Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia a pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia temporale, ſtet tono congiuntiſſimi con gl'<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>imperadori, &amp; dependendo con allegro animo dalla auto rità loro, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre che la digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta Imperiale ſi continuò ne deſcendenti di Carlo Mag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no: &amp; per la memoria de be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neficij dati &amp; riceuuti, &amp; per riſpetto della gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dezza imperiale: la quale poi decli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do, ſeparatiſi in tutto dal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la amicita loro, comincioro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no a fare profeſſione, che la dignità ponteficale, haueſſe piu toſto che a riceuere, a da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re le leggi alla imperiale: &amp; per cio hauendo ſopra tutte l'altre coſe in horrore el ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornare nell antica ſubiezzi one, et che eſſi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſsino di riconoſcere in Roma, et al troue l'antiche ragioni dell imperio, come alcuni di loro o di maggior potentia, o di ſpirito piu eleuato ſi Sforſa no di fare, ſi opponeuano ſco
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3676:31"/>
pertame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> le arme alla po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentia loro, accompagnati da quelli Tiranni, che ſotto nome de prencipi, &amp; da quel le cittàche vendicateſi in li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bertà, non ricognoſceuano piu l'autorità dell imperio. Daqueſto nacque che e pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifici attribuendoſi ogni di piu, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do el terrore delle arme ſpirituali alle co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe temporali, et interpretan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do che come vtcarij di Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto in terra, erano ſuperiori all'Jmper. et che a loro in molti coſi apparteneua la cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra dello ſtato terreno, priua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uano alcuna volta gl'imper. della dignità imperiale, ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citando gli Elettori a elegge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re de gl'altri in luogo de pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uati: &amp; dall'altra parte gl'Imper. o eleggeuano, o procu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rauano che ſi eleggeſſino nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oui pontefici: Da queſte con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſie nacque, eſſendo in debolito molto lo ſtato della Chieſa, ne meno per la dimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3676:32"/>
della corte Romana per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſettanta anni nella città d' Auignone &amp; per lo ſchiſma che al ritorno de pontifici ſuccedette in Italia, che nel le città ſottopoſte alla Chie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſa, &amp; ſpecialmente in quelle di Romagna, molti cittadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni potenti, occuparono nelle patrie proprie la tyrannide: è qualie pontifici o perſegui tauono, o non eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do potenti a opprimergli le concedeua no in feudo a quelli medeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi, o ſuſcita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do altri capi gl'inueſtiuano. Coſi comincia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rono le citta di Romagna ad hauere ſignori particola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ri, ſotto titolo, la maggior parte, di vicarij eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci. Coſi Ferrara data dal po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tefice in gouerno ad Azzo da Eſti, fu conceduta poi in titolo di vicariato, &amp; exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata in progreſſo di tempo quella famiglia a titoli piu illuſtri. Coſi Bologna occupa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta da Gioua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni Viſconte ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciueſcouo di Milano, gli fu
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3676:33"/>
poi conceduta in vicariato dal pontefice: et per le mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime cagioni in molte terre della Marca d'Ancona, del Patrimonio di ſan Piero, &amp; dell'Vmbria hora detto el Ducato dì Spoleto, ſurſono, o contro alla volontà, o con conſentimento quaſi sforza to de Pontefici, molti ſigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri particolari. le quali vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ationi, eſſendo ſimilmente ſopra venute in Lombardia alle citta dello imperio, acca dè tal volta che ſecondo la varieta delle coſe, e vicarij di Romagna, &amp; di altre ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re eccleſiaſtice, allont anateſi apertamente dal nome della Chieſa recognoſceuano in feudo quelle citta da gl'Jm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradori, come qual che vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta recognoſceuano in feudo da pontifici quelliche occupaua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o in Lombardia Milano, Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>toua, et altre terre imperiali. Et in queſti tempi Roma, be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che ritenendo in nome el domi nio della Chieſa, ſi reggeua
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3676:34"/>
per ſe ſteſſa: &amp; anchora che nel principio che e pontefici ritornorono d'Auignone in Jtalia fuſſino vbiditi come ſignori, nondimeno poco poi e Romani creato el magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrato de Bandereſi, ricaddo no nell'antica contumacia, do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de retene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>doui e pontefici piccoliſſima autorità, comin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciorono a non vi habitare in fino a ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to che e Romani im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poueriti, &amp; caduti: in grauiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſimi diſordini per l'abſentia della corte, &amp; approſſiman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſi l'anno del mille quattro ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, nel quale ſperauano, ſi à Roma fuſſe el pontefice, do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerui eſſere pel Giubelio, gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſſimo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corſo di tutta la Chriſtianità, ſupplicarono con humiliſſimi preghi à Bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifacio pontefice che vi ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornaſſe, offerendo di leuar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>via el magiſtrato de Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſi, &amp; di ſottometterſi in tutto alla obedientia ſua. Con le quali conditioni tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nato
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3676:35"/>
à Roma, intenti e Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani a guadagni di quello anno, preſo aſſolutamente lo imperio della citta, fortificò &amp; meſſe la guardia in caſtel ſant Angelo. e ſucceſſori del quale fino a Eugenio, benche vi haueſſeno ſpeſſo molte dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficulta, non dimeno fermato poi pienamente el dominio loro, e pontefici ſeguenti han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no ſenza alcuna co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſia ſignoreggiata a arbitrio ſuo quella citta. Con queſti fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damenti &amp; con queſti mezzi exaltati alla potentia terre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>na, depoſta apoco a poco la memoria della ſalute delle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime, &amp; de precetti diuini, &amp; voltati tuttie penſieri lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro alla grandezza mondana, ne vſando piu l'autorita ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rituale ſe non per inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to &amp; miniſterio della tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rale, cominciarono a parere piu toſto prencipi ſecolari, che pontefici: cominciarono a eſſere le cure &amp; i negotij loro non piu la ſantita
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3676:36"/>
della vita, non piu l'augmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to della religione, nou piuel zelo &amp; la carita verſo el proximo, ma exerciti, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerre contra a Chriſtiani, trattando copenſieri &amp; con le mani ſanguinoſe e ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij, ma accumulare di teſoro nuouo leggi, nuouo arti, nuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue inſidie per raccorre da og<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni parte danari, vſare à que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſto fine ſenza riſpetto l'arme ſpirituali, vendere a queſto fine ſenza vergogna le coſe ſacra et le profane:</p>
            <p>Le richezze diffuſe in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro et in tutta la corte ſegui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarano le pompe, el luxo &amp; i coſtumi inhoneſti, le libidinì &amp; i piaceri abomineuoli: neſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuna cura a ſucceſſori, neſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penſiero della maieſta perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua del pontificato: ma in lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ogo di queſto deſiderio ambi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioſo &amp; pestifero, di eſaltare non ſloamente a richezze
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3676:37"/>
immoderate, ma à principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, à regni e figliuoli e nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti &amp; congiunti loro, non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribuendo piu le dignita &amp; gl'emolumenti ne gl'huomi ni benemeriti et virtuoſi, ma quaſi ſempre o venden doſi al prezzo maggiore, o diſſipandoſi in perſone opor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tune al'ambitione, all'auari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia, o alle vergognoſe volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Per le quali' operationi perduta del tutto ne cuori del gl'huomini la reuerentia pontificale, ſi ſoſtenta no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meno in parte l'autorita per el nome &amp; per la maieſta ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to potente &amp; efficace della religione, &amp; aiutata molto dalla facultà che hanno di gratificare a prencipi gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, &amp; a quelli che ſono poten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ti appreſſo a loro per mezzo delle degnita, &amp; dell'altre conceſſioni eccleſiaſtiche. Donde congnoſcendoſi d'eſſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in ſommo riſpetto de gl'huomini, &amp; che a chi piglia
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3676:38"/>
l'arme contro à loro riſulta graue infamia, &amp; ſpeſſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitioni d'altri prencipi, &amp; in ogni euento picciolo guad agno, et che vincitori eſſerci tano la vittoria a arbitrio loro, vinti conſeguiſcono che conditione vogliono, &amp; ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulandoli la cupidita di ſol leuare e congiunti ſuoi di gradi priuati à principati, ſono ſtatida molto tempo in qua ſpeſſiſſime volte lo inſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mento di ſuſcitare guerre &amp; ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dij nuoui in Jtalia. Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritorna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do al principale pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſito noſtro, dal quale el do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore giuſtisſimo del danno publico m'hauena piu arden temente che non conuiene alla legge dell Hiſtoria tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portato, diciamo che, Le cit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta di Romagna veſſate, &amp;c</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3676:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
